<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="Release-Notes.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE release-history PUBLIC "-//UniTime//UniTime Release Notes DTD/EN" "Release-Notes.dtd">
<!--
 * Licensed to The Apereo Foundation under one or more contributor license
 * agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for
 * additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 *
 * The Apereo Foundation licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
 * Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
 * compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at:
 *
 * http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 *
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 *
 -->

<release-history>

<doc-title>UniTime 4.7 Release Notes</doc-title>
<release>
	<version>4.7.${build.number}</version>
	<release-date>${build.date}</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Wait-Listing</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					UniTime 4.7 includes various improvements in wait-listing,
					including the ability to swap a course or wait-list for a different section of a course that the student is already enrolled in.
				</line>
				<line>
					Also, there is a new Wait-List Preferences dialog that provides additional options to the student, including setting up a swap or
					providing section requirements.
				</line>
				<line>
					The course re-scheduling (automatic updates to student schedules after the course change) has been updated and
					made more robust. It also currently only triggers on courses that allow for wait-listing while the wait-listing is enabled.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Scheduling Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					UniTime 4.7 includes various improvements in student scheduling,
					including the ability for a student to indicate whether he/she prefers dense vs sparse schedule or online vs face-to-face classes.
				</line>
				<line>
					When enabled, a student may also require only online classes, or limit the days during which he/she can attend classes.
					<line>
						This is to better support Summer (or similar) sessions that contain multiple optional modules,
						and where students may be allowed to take some courses while not being present at the campus. 
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Override Requests: Course-specific Notes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Requests Override dialog updated to allow for course-specific notes.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Request Priorities</name>
			<description>
				<line>A new course request priority named Vital has been added.
					<line>The scale is now Critical &gt; Vital &gt; Important &gt; No Priority</line>
				</line>
				<line>Advisors can now set the course request priority separately from no-subs/wait-list toggle.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Funding Department</name>
			<description>
				<line>An optional funding department has been added to classes. It can be used to group the class data differently for funding reporting than it is done for course timetabling.</line>
				<line>The visibility of the funding department functionality is controlled by a property (unitime.courses.funding_departments_enabled) so it is not visible for institutions that do not use it.</line>
				<line>Finding department can be defined on multiple levels: on the subject area (for courses controlled by a course of this subject), on a course, or on an individual class.</line>
				<line>Similar to external managers, the funding department defaults to the controlling department of the class, and only departments marked as possible funding departments can be selected as additional options.</line>
				<line>A number of pages have been rewritten to GWT as part of this effort, but it is possible to switch the user interface back to the original Struts based page. See unitime.legacy.xxx properties in the Application Configuration.
					<line>These include Departments, Subject Areas, Instructor Assignment, and Add/Edit Course Offering pages.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Room Partitions</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to partition a room into multiple smaller rooms.
					<line>On the Add/Edit Room page, there is a new Partition of drop-down listing all rooms of the same building that are not partitions of some other rooms already.</line>
					<line>Non-university locations cannot be partitioned.</line>
					<line>On the Rooms page, there is a new Partitions of column (listing the parent room of room partition).</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added support for the course timetabling solver.
					<line>Parent room is unavailable when one of its partitions is occupied and vice versa (partitions cannot be used at the time when the parent class is occupied).</line>
					<line>Timetable Grid page can include:
						<line>classes from all the partitions on the parent room,</line>
						<line>classes of the parent room on each of the room partitions.</line>
						<line>This is disabled by default, enable by setting unitime.timeGrid.classesAcrossPartitions to true.</line>
					</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added support for conflict checking in the events, and for the computation and display of conflicting events.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Timetable Grid: Class Filter</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to filter classes that will be listed on the Timetable page.</line>
				<line>Enable by setting unitime.timeGrid.classFilter to true in the Application Configuration.</line>
				<line>The filter may contain a boolean expression (for example: ALG or BIOL or C S).</line>
				<line>The following tags are supported:
					<line>without any tags, both class name and instructor name are matched</line>
					<line>class: match class name only</line>
					<line>instructor: match instructor name or external id only</line>
					<line>room: match assigned room</line>
					<line>limit: match class limit (e.g., limit:>100 for classes over 100)</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Daybreak Distribution Constraint</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added Daybreak constraint that checks for cases when there is an evening class and a morning class the following day.</line>
				<line>There should be at least the given number of hours between an evening class followed by a morning class the next day.</line>
				<line>The constraint can be also parameterized by a distance between the two classes:
					<line>The constraint only triggers when the distance between the two classes is over the provided distance.</line>
					<line>Distance checking is disabled when distance is set to -1.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Other</title>
		<item>
			<name>Localization: Zanata &gt; POEditor.com</name>
			<description>
				<line>Since Zanata is no longer being maintained, UniTime 4.7 translations have been moved to poeditor.com.
					<line>See https://poeditor.com/join/project/Aa5qIUPsnp for joining the translations effort.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Single PO file per locale is now being used for data exchange.</line>
				<line>Updated ant tasks for import/export scripts, added ability to automatically download PO file and update UniTime.gwt.xml config.</line>
				<line>To build UniTime for a different language, for example German, just use
					<line>ant -Dlocale=de import-translations build</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>		
	</category>
</release>
</release-history>
