<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="Release-Notes.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE release-history PUBLIC "-//UniTime//UniTime Release Notes DTD/EN" "Release-Notes.dtd">
<!-- 
 * Licensed to The Apereo Foundation under one or more contributor license
 * agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for
 * additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 *
 * The Apereo Foundation licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
 * Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
 * compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at:
 *
 * http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 *
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 * 
 -->

<release-history>

<doc-title>UniTime 4.1 Release Notes</doc-title>

<release>
	<version>4.1.${build.number}</version>
	<release-date>${build.date}</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Batch Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Minimal Perturbation Mode</name>
			<description>
				<line>In priority and equal weigthing, the difference of an enrollment (from the initial one) is computed as an average using the following schema:
					<line>an initial section counts as 1</line>
					<line>same choice section counts as 0.9 (parameter StudentWeights.SameChoice)</line>
					<line>same time section counts as 0.7 (parameter StudentWeights.SameTime)</line>
					<line>different time section counts as 0</line>
				</line>
				<line>Non-initial enrollment weight is penalized with weight StudentWeights.Perturbation (defaults to 0.100).</line>
				<line>When MPP is enabled, solution info contains the following three new properties:
					<line>Perturbations: same section assigned (% of initial section assigned over all course requests with initial enrollment)</line>
					<line>Perturbations: same choice assigned (% of same time and instructor section assigned over all course requests with initial enrollment)</line>
					<line>Perturbations: same time assigned (% of same time section assigned over all course requests with initial enrollment)</line>
				</line>
				<line>When Sectioning.KeepInitialAssignments is set to true (defaults to false), only the initial value is in the variable’s domain (when there is an initial value).
					<line>Also there is a new global constraint (named FixInitialAssignments) that prevents unassignment of an initial value by another global constraint (limits, reservations).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Request Groups</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to keep students of the same group together.</line>
				<line>Measured as an average probability of two students (of a group) that are requesting the same course being given the same section (of the same subpart).</line>
				<line>There is a new weight (named StudentWeights.SameGroup, defaults to 0.1) expressing how much this criterion affects the student weight (in both priority and equal weighting).
					<line>This means that if a student is being enrolled into a completely different section, weight of such an enrollment is decreased by 10%
						(the metric reflects how much are the students spread between the sections of the course).</line>
				</line>
				<line>There is a new Request Groups report on the Student Scheduling Solver Reports page.</line>
				<line>Request groups are loaded in only when the solver paramter Load.RequestGroups is set to true, default is false</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
</release-history>