<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="Release-Notes.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE release-history PUBLIC "-//UniTime//UniTime Release Notes DTD/EN" "Release-Notes.dtd">
<!--
 * Licensed to The Apereo Foundation under one or more contributor license
 * agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for
 * additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 *
 * The Apereo Foundation licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
 * Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
 * compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at:
 *
 * http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 *
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 *
 -->

<release-history>

<doc-title>UniTime 4.8 Release Notes</doc-title>
<release>
	<version>4.8.${build.number}</version>
	<release-date>${build.date}</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Instructor Survey</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added a new page (Instructor Survey) that can be used by instructors to fill in their preferences and course requirements.</line>
				<line>To be enabled by the Instructor Survey toggle on the academic session status page (Status Types page).</line>
				<line>See https://help48.unitime.org/instructor-survey for more details.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Online Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Online Student Scheduling Dashboard: Advisor Recommendation</name>
			<description>
				<line>In the table showing the advisor recommendations for a student, added the following two columns:
					<line>Advised: date and time when the line was added or modified last</line>
					<line>Advisor: person who advised the student (who added/modified the line last)</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Finder, Online Scheduling Dashboard</name>
			<description>
				<line>When showing data direcly from the database (online scheduling server is not running)
					<line>Correct date pattern formatting (using unitime.pattern.format.useDates property)</line>
					<line>Include date pattern and required room for arrange hours classes</line>
					<line>This applies to
						<line>List of classes on the Course Finder dialog</line>
						<line>Enrollments of a student on the online dashboard (Student dialog)</line>
						<line>Classes listed on the Enrollments tab</line>
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Finder: Filter</name>
			<description>
				<line>Course Finder dialog on the Scheduling Assistant, Course Requests, and Advisor Course Recommendations pages improved.</line>
				<line>Added Filter section, which allows for filtering courses by:
					<line>Class start/end date (given course must have an enrollment that does not start before the given From date, or lasts past the To date)</line>
					<line>Min/max credit</line>
					<line>Instructor name (given course must have a class with matching instructor name)</line>
				</line>
				<line>Notes:
					<line>Classes that do not display instructors are not considered by the instructor filter.</line>
					<line>Classes that are not enabled for student scheduling are ignored (both instructor and class dates filters).</line>
					<line>The filter is ONLY used for the list of courses, it does not guarantee that the student gets a class with the given instructor or within the given dates.</line>
					<line>When used on the Student Course Requests page or Advisor Course Recommendations page at the time when the schedule of classes has not been published yet,
						only allow for credit filter (no filtering by class dates or instructor names until the schedule of classes is published).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Scheduling Dashboards: Show/Hide Columns</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to show/hide columns on the dashboard tables (Enrollments, Students, and Change Log).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Scheduling Rules</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added student scheduling rules that can be used to define which courses a particular group of students can request/enroll in.These rules can be defined on Administration > Other > Student Scheduling Rules page.</line>
				<line>A group of students can be a student filter (same format as on the dashboards, e.g., group:SpecialStudents or primary-major:%-OL).</line>
				<line>Each group of students can be restricted to particular course types (provided using a regular expression, e.g., !No Pre-Reg),
					course names (provided using a regular expression, e.g, .*[0-9]OL for all courses with OL suffix),
					or instructional methods (provided using a regular expression, e.g., PO|PH for course configurations with PO or PH instructional methods).
					<line>A course name or instructional method regular expression can be negated by using an exclamation mark as a prefix (e.g., !.*[0-9]OL for all courses without an OL suffix).</line>
					<line>If multiple expressions are provided (e.g., both course and instructional method), depending on the mode of the rule, all of the expressions must match or just one.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Each rule can be restricted by a regular expression matching academic initiative, a regular expression matching term, start and end year.</line>
				<line>The rules are processed in the given order.</line>
				<line>For each student, the first matching rule is used (there are no course or instructional method restrictions when no rule applies).</line>
				<line>A rule can apply only to filter (ability to lookup a course), online scheduling, and/or batch scheduling.Advisors and/or admins may be allowed to ignore the rule (there could be special courses that only advisors and/or admins can put the students in).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>	
	<category>
		<title>Batch Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Solver Load: Replace Pending courses with Substitutes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to treat substitute course demands as primary when a primary course demand was skipped entirely due to one of the following reasons:
					<line>pending override request (when Load.ReplacePendingWithSubstitute is true, defaults to false)</line>
					<line>canceled override request (when Load.ReplaceCancelledWithSubstitute is true, defaults to false)</line>
					<line>rejected override request (when Load.ReplaceRejectedWithSubstitute is true, defaults to false)</line>
					<line>not offered course (when Load.ReplaceNotOfferedWithSubstitute is true, defaults to false)</line>
				</line>
				<line>More precisely, when a course demand is skipped (all its courses are skipped for some reason),
					and at least one of the courses is skipped due to a reason that is enabled, then
					<line>Take the top most substitute course demand and treat it as primary.</line>
					<line>The position of the substitute course is kept (it shows at the bottom of the primary requests instead of at the top of the substitutes).</line>
				</line>
				<line>Course demands that do not allow for substitutes (Wait-List or No-Sub toggle is checked) are not replaced with a substitute.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Batch Student Solver Reports: Solution Statistics</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added Requested Courses - impossible row: percentage of requested courses that have no possible enrollment (e.g., due to having all classes disabled).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Bug Fixes</title>
		<item>
			<name>Academic Sessions</name>
			<description>
				<line>Academic Session column: use academic year (instead of session start year) when identifying an academic session.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Examination PDF Reports, Enrollment Audit PDF Reports</name>
			<description>
				<line>Use academic year (instead of session start year) when naming an output file.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructor Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>Previous/Next buttons on the Instructor Detail page: follow the order in which the instructors were listed on the Instructors page.
					<line>Instead of using the default order (instructor names).</line>
				</line>
				<line>Also applies to Previous/Next buttons on the Edit Instructor, Instructor Assignment Preferences, and Instructor Preferences pages.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>	
</release>
</release-history>
