<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="Release-Notes.css"?>
<!-- 
 * UniTime 3.0 (University Course Timetabling & Student Sectioning Application)
 * Copyright (C) 2007, UniTime.org
 * 
 * This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
 * it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
 * the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
 * (at your option) any later version.
 * 
 * This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
 * but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 * MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
 * GNU General Public License for more details.
 * 
 * You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 * with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 * 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA.
 -->

<release-history>

<doc-title>Timetabling - Release Notes</doc-title>

<!-- When a release date is not available or to be decided use the tag @release.date@ -->

<release>
	<version>2.5.2</version>
	<release-date>@release.date@</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Notes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Schedule Notes on Course Offering and Class renamed to Schedule of Classes Notes and Student Schedule Note</line>
				<line>Note on Instructional Offering list renamed to Note to Schedule Manager</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Crosslists</name>
			<description>
				<line>Adding to / removing from a cross list preserves the attributes such as title, schedules note, etc</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Help</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added help pages FAQ and Tips &amp; Tricks.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Managers</name>
			<description>
				<line>List of manages: added a column containing managed solver groups.</line>
				<line>Edit manager: added ability to add/remove solver group to/from a manager.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Distribution Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added possibility to restrict usage of distribution preferences of certain types to given departments.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offerings</name>
			<description>
				<line>Sorting capability added.</line>
				<line>If user settings 'Sort classes on detail pages' is set to yes, 
					<line>sorting from Instructional Offerings page is reused on Instrictional Offering Detail page and on Assign Instructors page and</line>
					<line>sorting from Classes page is reused on Scheduling Subpart Detail page.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Add new offering now redirects to Course Offering Edit screen</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offering Detail, Scheduling Subpart Detail, Class Detail, Instructor Detail, Room Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>Functionality of Back button improved: the previous page is loaded and scrolled down to the appropriate item.
					<line>When returning to Instructional Offerings page (from class or scheduling subpart), the page is scrolled down to the appropriate instructional offering 
					rather than class or subpart.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Add/Edit Room Group, Add/Edit Room Feature, Add/Edit Distribution Preference</name>
			<description>
				<line>Functionality of Back/Update/Add New buttons improved: the previous page is loaded and scrolled down to the appropriate item.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>All Pages</name>
			<description>
				<line>Message 'Page loaded in X sec.' changed to 'Page generated in X sec.'.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Administration / Departments</name>
			<description>
				<line>List of departments: added sorting capadilities, added collumns External Manager and Dist Pref Priority.</line>
				<line>Edit department: added distribution preference priority and external manager.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offerings, Classes, Instructors, Rooms</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to display time preference and room sharing grid as text.
					<line>To do so, change user settings 'Time Grid Display Format' to 'text'.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Text representation is now also available as tooltip of the displayed room sharing / time preference thumbnail.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Distribution Types</name>
			<description>
				<line>Constraint 'Next Day' added
					<line>The second class has to be placed on the following day of the first class (if the first class is on Friday, second class have to be on Monday).</line>
					<line>When prohibited or (strongly) discouraged: The second class has to be placed on the previous day of the first class (if the first class is on Monday, second class have to be on Friday).</line>
					<line>Note: This constraint works only between pairs of classes.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Constraint 'Two Days After' added
					<line>The second class has to be placed two days after the first class (Monday -> Wednesday, Tuesday -> Thurday, Wednesday -> Friday, Thursday -> Monday, Friday -> Tuesday).</line>
					<line>When prohibited or (strongly) discouraged: The second class has to be placed two days before the first class (Monday -> Thursday, Tuesday -> Friday, Wednesday -> Monday, Thursday -> Tuesday, Friday -> Wednesday).</line>
					<line>Note: This constraint works only between pairs of classes.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Solution Commit/Uncommit</name>
			<description>
				<line>Notification email is sent to SMAS Ops.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Reports</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Room allocation report improved:
					<line>If two classes are meeting together, only one is now counted.</line>
					<line>Date patterns are considered (e.g., the number of hours allocated by a Week 1-8 class is multiplied by 8/15).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Div-Sec Numbers</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Computation of div-sec numbers improved: In order to prevent division numbers to exceed 99 
					(e.g., because of the attempt to consider parent-child relations) the following two fallbacks were created:
					<line>If division number 100 is reached, div-sec numbers for the given subpart are recomputed, 
						without considering parent-child relations.</line>
					<line>If division number 100 is still reached, div-sec numbers for the given subpart are recomputed, 
						now considering all classes from all subparts with the same itype of all configurations together. 
						(This means that it can end up with, e.g., two recitations with the same division number even if 
						they are of diferent configurations of an instructional offering -- ENGL 106 case with 5 x 60 
						recitations of 1x50 time pattern -- without this fallback, 20 different division numbers are 
						needed for each config.)</line>
				</line>
				<line>
					Order classes within the same section number based on class sequence number rather than assigned room 
					to ensure better matching between section numbers of parent and children classes.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Department Comparator</name>
			<description>
				<line>Order external departments by distribution preference priority (i.e., the order in which the appropriate problems are to be solved).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>User Roles</name>
			<description>
				<line>New role 'View All' added.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Time Patterns</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Break time added: meeting endTime (that is to be printed in the UI) is then startTime + 5 * slotsPerMtg - breakTime
				</line>
				<line>
					Exact time: relation between number of minutes per meeting and number of time slots per meeting / break time 
					can be defined in the database (table EXACT_TIME_MINS).
					<line>
						Added user interface for editing of this relation (admin only).
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>User Rights</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					The following rules have been added in order to prohibit user to create or delete a class that is not editable by the user 
					(i.e., ownership of those classes have been transfered to an external manager):
					<line>
						User cannot make a course not offered when some of its classes are not editable by the user.
					</line>
					<line>
						User cannot duplicate a configuration that has classes that are not editable by the user.
					</line>
					<line>
						User cannot add a course that has classes that are not editable by the user into a cross-list of another course.
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.5.1</version>
	<release-date>27-Dec-2006</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Scheduling Subpart Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added option to clear all class preferences.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Help</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added help pages FAQ and Tips &amp; Tricks.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Managers</name>
			<description>
				<line>List of manages: added a column containing managed solver groups.</line>
				<line>Edit manager: added ability to add/remove solver group to/from a manager.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Distribution Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Added constraint 'Children Cannot Overlap'
					<line>If parent classes do not overlap in time, children classes can not overlap in time as well.</line>
					<line>Note: This constraint only needs to be put on the parent classes. Preferred configurations are Required All Classes or Pairwise (Strongly) Preferred.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.5.0</version>
	<release-date>20-Dec-2006</release-date>
	<release-description>First release of version 2.5</release-description>
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.4.19</version>
	<release-date>19-Dec-2006</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Class Setup</name>
			<description>
				<line>Class Setup page changed to show limit instead of min and max limit unless a variable limit exists or allow variable limits is selected.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offering Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>Edit Configuration / Duplicate buttons are only present when the instructional offering is offered.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Classes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Display course number suggestions when a single subject area is selected.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offerings, Reservations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Include non-controlling courses in the course number suggestions.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.4.18</version>
	<release-date>16-Dec-2006</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Class / Scheduling Subpart / Instructional Offering Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Table of distribution preferences: do not display instructor distribution preference in the case 
					when all classes assigned to the instructor are externally managed (distribution preference has no meaning in this case).
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Database Loader</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Do not load instructor distribution preference in the case when all classes assigned to the instructor are 
					externally managed (distribution preference has no meaning in this case).
				</line>
				<line>
					Warning "Class limit exceeded for class C" computed more precisely, i.e., a class limit can be exceeded, 
					but less than the weight of the weightiest student in the group.
				</line>
			</description>
			<name>Initial Sectioning</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Fixed a problem in initial sectioning -- weighted number of enrolled students could exceed class 
					limit (by one student) in certain cases.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>	
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.4.17</version>
	<release-date>14-Dec-2006</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Add/Edit Instructor -- Lookup</name>
			<description>
				<line>Display instructor name in the same format as on Manage Instructors page (Staff File Matches).</line>
				<line>Display instructor's department (Staff File Matches, display department abbreviation if available, department code otherwise).</line>
				<line>Order instructors by position (Staff File Matches).</line>
				<line>Display instructors in a table (with similar format as on Manager Instructors page) rather than having just a list of instructors with some notes in brackets next to each of them.</line>
				<line>When an instructor is selected (Staff File Matches) and position is not yet filled in on Add/Edit Instructor page, populate position from the staff file.</line>
				<line>Removed FTE field</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructor List</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Display column Designator instead of FTE.
					<line>Only designator codes for subject areas inside the selected department are displayed.</line>
					<line>Instructors table can be ordered by designator column.</line>
					<line>In the case of just one subject area (within the selected department) -> display designator code only.</line>
					<line>In the case of multiple subject areas -> display designator code plus respective subject arreas in the brackets, for example (designator code 2 for FLL and JPNS subject areas, 3 for LATN):
						<line>2 (FLL, JPNS)</line>
						<line>3 (LATN)</line></line></line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructor Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Designator list: do not change mouse pointer to hand on read-only lines.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Class Edit/Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					When a class is set to have unlimited enrollment (e.g., independent studies), allow room preference 
					(but only room preference, not building, room feature or room group preferences) to be set on a class 
					or inherited from subpart or instructor -> will be exported back to MSF as room assignment.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Inquiry</name>
			<description>
				<line>Submit Inquiry renamed to Contact Us.</line>
				<line>Contact information added.</line>
				<line>When an inquiry is submitted, a conformation email is send to the user.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Timetable</name>
			<description>
				<line>Include Sunday in Day filter.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Administration / Timetable Managers</name>
			<description>
				<line>Memorize table order within http session.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Administration / Solver Groups</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added committed solution date.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Room Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>The following message has been added under the Room Availability table (if room is editable):
					<line>Room Availability table is read-only. To edit this table, please click Edit Room Availability button.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Designators, Rooms, Room Groups, Room Features</name>
			<description>
				<line>Corrected ability to create a new designator, room, room group, room feature in the case when the user controls multiple departments, but only some of them are editable by the user.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Distribution Preferneces</name>
			<description>
				<line>Corrected ability to create / update a distribution preference in the case when the user controls multiple departments, but only some of them are editable by the user.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<title>INPUT DATA</title>
		<item>
			<name>Departments</name>
			<description>
				<line>Department 0001 Entrepreneurship (with subject area ENTR) created.</line>
				<line>Department 0002 Honors (with subject area HONR) created.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Department Status</name>
			<description>
				<line>Limited editability (class instructor assignment) is disabled when timetable is published.</line>
				<line>Departmental states that are to be set on externally managed departments are renamed to:
					<line>External Mgr. Input Data Entry</line>
					<line>External Mgr. Timetabling</line>
					<line>External Mgr. Timetable Published</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added two new departmental states (to be set on "normal" departments):
					<line>'Department Read Only' -- given department can not edit or timetable (even when it is allowed by session status)</line>
					<line>'Department Allow Edit' -- given department can edit or timetable (even when it is prohibited by session status)</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Date Patterns</name>
			<description>
				<line>Include a whole month before semester starts and after semester ends (i.e., July - January for Fall term).</line>
				<line>Months displayed in a table of 4 x 2 (was 3 x 2).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>	
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.4.16</version>
	<release-date>09-Dec-2006</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Rooms</name>
			<description>
				<line>List of departments: externally managed departments moved at the bottom of the list.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Class Edit/Detail, Classes, Instructional Offerings</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					When number of rooms on a class is set to zero (e.g., independent studies), allow room preference 
					(but only room preference, not building, room feature or room group preferences) to be set on a class 
					or inherited from a subpart or an instructor -> will be exported back to MSF as room assignment.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Inquiry</name>
			<description>
				<line>New category "LLR/LAB data entry is done" added.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Configuration Edit</name>
			<description>
				<line>One limit is displayed by default. User can select option 'Variable Limits' to specify min and max limits.</line>
				<line>Created an user setting that hides the option 'Variable Limits' by default</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>INPUT DATA</title>
		<item>
			<name>Room Sharing</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Ownership (controlling department) of all rooms that are being shared between two departments, 
					from which one is 1979 (Smas - General Academic Classrooms) was changed from department 1979 to 
					the other department (the other department that the room is being shared with).
				</line>
				<line>
					All rooms that are shared by department 1980 (Smas - General University) are now also shared 
					with LLR department (1994).
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>New External (Managing) Departments</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					External manager 'Cont. &amp; Distance Education Mgr' (department 1589) created.
					<line>To handle X courses.</line>
					<line>All rooms that are shared with department 1979 (Smas - General Academic Classrooms) are shared with this department (1589) as well.</line>
					<line>To be solved after departmental problems.</line>
				</line>
				<line>
					External manager 'Engineering Prof. Ed. Manager' (department 1302) created.
					<line>Rooms: POTR 262, POTR 268</line>
					<line>There is still a question whether this problem will be solved before or after departmental problems.</line>
				</line>
				<line>
					External manager 'Need Classroom Manager' (department 1979) created.
					<line>To handle need room requests.</line>
					<line>Rooms: All classrooms of the department 1979 (Smas - General Academic Classrooms).</line>
					<line>To be solved after departmental problems.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>	
	<category>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Constraint Solver</name>
			<description>
				<line>Open-source library ifs-1.1_b13 is being used.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>	
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.4.15</version>
	<release-date>06-Dec-2006</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Add Special Use Room</name>
			<description>
				<line>No department was assigned when it was used by administrator.</line>
				<line>Fixed problem with hibernate cache (a room was not displayed right after it was created).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Solver Server</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed problem with the solvers not being able to access the database after restart of the database server.
					<line>Apache DBCP connection pool is now used by solver servers.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>	
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.4.14</version>
	<release-date>05-Dec-2006</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Rooms</name>
			<description>
				<line>Caption of the button 'Add Non-University Location' corrected.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offerings</name>
			<description>
				<line>Display full course title in the tool tip of the course.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Assign Instructors</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to assign multiple instructors to a class.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Date Pattern</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed problems with disappearing default date pattern.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>	
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.4.13</version>
	<release-date>05-Dec-2006</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offering Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed problem with duplicities in Distribution Preferences table (caused by Preference comparator).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Scheduling Subpart Detail/Edit</name>
			<description>
				<line>Field 'Parent Scheduling Subpart' was not containing the subpart's sufix (e.g., in case of COM 114 Lec (a) only COM 114 Lec was printed).</line>
				<line>Subpart's sufix was also not present in the navigation bar.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Class Edit</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed hibernate cache problem which sometimes occurs when an instructor is deleted: unable to load a ClassInstructor object.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructor Edit</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed hibernate cache problem when an instructor is deleted: unable to load a DepartmentalInstructor object on Instructor Assignment page.</line>
				<line>Fixed hibernate cache problem when an instructor is created: instructor is not present on Instructor Assignment page.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructor Assignment</name>
			<description>
				<line>Display instructors within a class in a correct order (if there are two or more instructors on a class).</line>
				<line>Fixed IndexOutOfBoundsException thrown when the very last instructor of the very last class is deleted.</line>
				<line>Fixed hibernate cache problem: assigned classes are not visible on the list of instructors.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Distribution Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>Wildcard charcter ( * ) supported when specifying course number</line>
				<line>Course number search is case-insensitive (205h and 205H return the same results)</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offerings, Classes, Reservations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Course number search is case-insensitive (205h and 205H return the same results)</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructors, Manage Instructors</name>
			<description>
				<line>FTEs are aligned to the right and displayed as a percentage</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructor Lookup</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed bug that discarded the last name if any instructor had 2 or more middle names</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Timetables, Solver</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added conformation dialog for operations Unload, Commit, Uncommit and Save.</line>
				<line>Committed solution cannot be deleted -- it has to be uncommitted first.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Distribution Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>Group constraint 'More Than 1 Day Between' added
					<line>Given classes must have more two or more days in between.</line>
					<line>When prohibited or (strongly) discouraged: given classes must be offered on adjacent days or with at most one day in between.</line>
				</line>
				<line>For sequence constraints (Back-To-Back, x Hours Between etc.), checking for conflicts is improved as follows:
					<line>
						Fixed a problem with the returned set of conflicting placements not being correct in some special cases
						(e.g., BTB over three classes, Lec 1 M 7:30, Lec 2 M 8:30, placing Lec 3 M 12:30 invalidated only Lec 2, but Lec 1 is conflicting as well).
					</line>
					<line>
						The returned set of conflicting placements follows the specification of partial satisfaction of a constraint more precisely:
						<line>
							A (partially assigned) constraint is partially satisfied if the existing assignment can be extended into a complete assignment satisfying the constraint.
						</line>
						<line>
							Computation of conflicting placements returns the minimal set (using cardinality) of placements that makes the constraint partially satisfied when unassigned.
						</line>
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Added ability to specify neighbour selection criterion</name>
			<description>
				<line>Standard implementation selects a variable and one of its values using the existing variable and value selection criteria.</line>
				<line>However, this makes the solver more general (each iteration is no longer limited to select and (re)assign just one variable).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Automated Solver</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					New neighbour selection metaheuristics: with a given probability, select the best suggestion 
					(computed within a given depth and time limit) instead of the existing selection of a variable and its value.
				</line>
				<line>
					While fixing the best complete solution, use the suggestions technique (an improving best suggestion is computed within 
					a depth of 2 and given time limit for each class) to improve the solution even further.
				</line>
				<line>
					These changes can significantly improve the performance of the solver, especially in the case when 
					there is a lot of distribution preferences in the problem (e.g., COM 114 problem is solved within 5 minutes, with more than 77% 
					strongly preferred same room constraints satisfied).
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Computation of DIV-SEC numbers</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Do not reuse divisions when there are less than 100 classes in a scheduling subpart.
				</line>
				<line>
					Follow parent-child relations when there are less than 100 classes
					<line>
						All classes of the same parent will have division numbers from the same interval
						(e.g., Rec 1-1..4-1 under Lec 1-1, Rec 5-1..8-1 under Lec 2-1)
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.4.12</version>
	<release-date>30-Nov-06</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Release Notes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Release notes introduced</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Menu</name>
			<description>
				<line>'Help Manual' renamed to 'Help'</line>
				<line>Menu Item 'Submit Inquiry' was moved under section 'Help'</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offerings</name>
			<description>
				<line>Credit information abbreviated (e.g. '3 SH CC' for '3 Semester Hours of Collegiate Credit')</line>
				<line>Consent abbreviated (prefix 'Consent of ' removed, e.g., 'Department' for 'Consent of Department')</line>
				<line>Added optional Designator Required column</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Class / Scheduling Subpart Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>Distribution row removed from class / subpart preferences (it is only relevant for Instructor Detail page).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Manage Instructor List</name>
			<description>
				<line>Instructor list is sorted by position relevance (Professor, Associate Professor ...).</line>
				<line>Instructor name is displayed in one column and in the format Last, First Middle</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Rooms, Room Groups, Room Features, Instructors, Designator List</name>
			<description>
				<line>Export PDF function added.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Database Loader</name>
			<description>
				<line>Do not print warning "Same instructor and overlapping time required between classes C1 and C2" when both classes are being taught in the same room (or set of rooms) and there is Can Share Room constraint posted between these classes.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.4.11</version>
	<release-date>22-Nov-06</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Submit Inquiry</name>
			<description>
				<line>A page to submit user inquiry was added under menu Help Manual. This can be used to submit a category-specific email to Timetabling administrators</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Suggestions</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed problem which displays a minimal room size of '2147483647'</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Configuration Edit</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed bug caused by loading of configurations with no subparts attached to it</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>

	<category>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Struts</name>
			<description>
				<line>Apache Struts was updated to version 1.2.9</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>build.xml</name>
			<description>
				<line>Build of Timetabling.war initaly had all the classes archived in timetable.jar. The classes are now not archived but exist in exploded form</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Error Email</name>
			<description>
				<line>Email configuration for sending error messages is set in the file application.properties</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.4.10</version>
	<release-date>21-Nov-06</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Help Manuals</name>
			<description>
				<line>Updated help manuals</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>

	<category>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Network Connection</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed problem with sockets on IBM AIX Java 1.4 (Socket.isConnected() is always false)</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>2.4.9</version>
	<release-date>20-Nov-06</release-date>
	<release-description>Production release of version 2.4 (release for Fall 07 Timetabling)</release-description>
</release>

</release-history>