<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="Release-Notes.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE release-history PUBLIC "-//UniTime//UniTime Release Notes DTD/EN" "Release-Notes.dtd">
<!-- 
 * UniTime 3.4 (University Timetabling Application)
 * Copyright (C) 2008 - 2012, UniTime LLC
 * 
 * This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
 * it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
 * the Free Software Foundation; either version 3 of the License, or
 * (at your option) any later version.
 * 
 * This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
 * but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 * MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
 * GNU General Public License for more details.
 * 
 * You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 * with this program.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
 * 
 -->

<release-history>

<doc-title>UniTime 3.4 Release Notes</doc-title>

<release>
	<version>3.4.${build.number}</version>
	<release-date>${build.date}</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Other Improvements</title>
		<item>
			<name>Curriculum Timetabling</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to provide parameters for the curriculum solver (student conversion).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Add / Edit Event</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added confirmation of a change in the event contact information (main contact).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>HQL Reports</name>
			<description>
				<line>Print: print the whole report (not just what is visible on the page, limited to 10,000 lines).</line>
				<line>Corrected sorting query / browser history when sorting in descendant order.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>3.4.299</version>
	<release-date>Sat, 9 Nov 2013</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Bug Fixes</title>
		<item>
			<name>Event Filter</name>
			<description>
				<line>Requested By: mouse clicking on a suggested name did not update the filter.</line>
				<line>Requested By: removed duplicate suggestions.</line>
				<line>After / Before: mouse clicking on a suggested time should not close the filter.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Class Assignment</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed a lazy initialization exception that was sometimes thrown when there was an instructor with no external id assigned to the class.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Events</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed daylight saving time issues (ServerTimeZone did not include DST transitions).</line>
				<line>Fixed a failed to load exception when an event that has a meeting with no location is clicked.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>3.4.291</version>
	<release-date>Fri, 18 Oct 2013</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Bug Fixes</title>
		<item>
			<name>Add / Edit Event</name>
			<description>
				<line>Course Related Event: at least one related object (a class, a configuration, a course offering, or an instructional offering) is required.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Timetabling: Distribution Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed NullPointerException when removing an existing constraints from the model during the data load (e.g., because it is posted between committed variables).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offerings, Classes: PDF Export</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed condition for printing class schedule print note and class note to schedule manager in full length.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Timetabling: Timetable Grid</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed formatting issues when there are too many instructors assigned to a class by imposing maximal cell widths.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Events: Event Rooms</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed the case when there is no status set on the department + room type level (the RoomTypeOption entity does not exist).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Classes, Class Assignments</name>
			<description>
				<line>Timetable (class time and room assignments) was not shown when the data were loaded into a solver that was running on a remote solver server.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Permission</name>
			<description>
				<line>Users with Status Independent permission can approve / reject / cancel meetings in a room that does not allow for approval (it is in one of the Events Managers No Approval states).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Class Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>Committed assignment was wrongly displayed for a class when the selected solution did not contain an assignment for the class.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Manage Solvers</name>
			<description>
				<line>Wrong permission check prevented the page from showing solvers from other academic sessions (only solvers from the current academic session were shown).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Online Student Scheduling: Suggestions</name>
			<description>
				<line>Do not print a warning message about a section not being available anymore when the user holds an individual reservation for it.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>GWT: Uncaught Exception</name>
			<description>
				<line>Do not show the red notification popup when there is an uncaught exception seen, only log it as a warning.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Solver Changes</title>
		<item>
			<name>Course Timetabling: Room Ratio</name>
			<description>
				<line>Store room ratio in float precision (as it is done in UniTime) to avoid different number precision issues.
					<line>This fixes the issue with meet together constraint failing to assign two classes of 20 (with room ration 0.8) into a room of 32 due to the increased precision in the room ratio.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Other Improvements</title>
		<item>
			<name>Events, Event Room Availability, Event Timetable</name>
			<description>
				<line>Room / Event Filter: Added ability to store current room / event filter settings as default (for the user and page).
					<line>This can be done by clicking on a little star icon (usually denoting favorites) in the bottom right corner of the filter pop up.</line>
					<line>Clear button resets the filter settings to the (previously saved) default value.</line> 
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Add Event</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to define default value for Additional Emails field.
					<line>In menu, Preferences &gt; Event Defaults (needs permission EventDefaults).</line>
					<line>Users with EventDefaultsEditOther permission can see / modify defaults for other users.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Management: Unusual Times</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to indicate that a meeting is on an unusual time (too early).</line>
				<line>If the application property unitime.event.tooEarly is set (default is not set), it indicates the last time slot that is considered too early (e.g., 72 means 6 am).</line>
				<line>A meeting is considered too early when:
					<line>it starts after midnight, but before the given time (e.g., 6am), or</line>
					<line>it starts at midnight and ends before or at the given time.</line>
				</line>
				<line>If a meeting is too early, it is marked bold orange in the List of Events and List of Meetings.</line>
				<line>There is also a warning message "The requested time is unusual, please look at it closely." displayed on the second page of the Add Meetings dialog and below the meeting on the Add / Edit Event page.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Events: Event Filter</name>
			<description>
				<line>Requested By field of the Event Filter now provides suggestions as the main contact's name or email address is typed in.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Application Config</name>
			<description>
				<line>Permission Application Config split into two:
					<line>Application Config: allows to view the Application Config page (without any modification capabilities),</line>
					<line>Application Config Edit: allows to make changes as well.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Session Status Types</name>
			<description>
				<line>Allow Roll Forward permission: an academic session can only be rolled forwarded into an academic session of a status that allows for roll forward.
					<line>This replaces the previous (less general) behavior where the target academic session had to have the initial status (status with the reference set to 'initial', usually called Initial Data Load).</line>
					<line>Only the initial status type has this permission enabled by default, but this enables other academic session statuses to allow for roll forward as well.</line> 
				</line>
				<line>Allow No Role permission: users without any other UniTime role are allowed to select an academic session of this status using the No Role role.
					<line>This replaces the previous (less general) behavior where the academic session had to be identified as active (from other permissions).</line>
					<line>No Role role must be also enabled for this permission to make any difference.</line> 
				</line>
				<line>Together, the two new permissions allow to better handle the case when an academic session is rolled forward in two phases (up to the rooms first, all the rest much later), with the event management enabled after the first phase. </line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>3.4.275</version>
	<release-date>Sat, 17 Aug 2013</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Bug Fixes</title>
		<item>
			<name>Academic Session Roll Forward</name>
			<description>
				<line>Rooms roll forward: set event status of the newly copied rooms to blank.
					<line>This means that the event status of all the rooms in the new academic session will default to what is set on the departments for each room type (which is already reset to No Event Management).</line>
					<line>This is to prevent the rooms from being immediately available to event management.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>User Context: Current Academic Session</name>
			<description>
				<line>On the first date of an academic session, a wrong default academic session may be selected for a user. This has been fixed.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Classes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed a permission glitch which prevented schedule deputies to see a committed timetable when the course timetabling is finished (academic session does not allow for course timetabling).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offerings</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed return URL when only one subject area is available and none is selected.
					<line>The issue was causing the Subject Area is required error message (when going back from an Instructional Offering Detail page) and clearing all toggles of the Filter section.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Add / Edit Event</name>
			<description>
				<line>Main contact email address verification has been added.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Events: Event Filter</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to lookup events by the requestor's email address (for users with Event Lookup Contact or Event Lookup Schedule permission). Just enter the email address in the Requested By field or start typing the email address in to get suggestions.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>LDAP Authentication</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to control whether the role (used as the user's external unique id in UniTime) will be converted to upper case.
					<line>There is a new application property unitime.authentication.ldap.group-convert-to-uppercase (defaults to false, no conversion).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Accommodations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Student Accommodations (Administration): Added page Student Accommodations where student accommodations / special needs can be managed (very much like with the Student Groups).</line>
				<line>Instructional Offering Detail, Class Detail, Examination Detail, Event Detail: Enrollments table shows student accommodations, if there are any (column Accommodation is only visible if there is at least one student with an accommodation).</line>
				<line>Instructional Offering Detail, Class Detail, Examination Detail: If there are any student accommodations, short overview table (accommodation name plus the number of students in the offering / class / exam) is also present at the bottom of the top most section.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Other Improvements</title>
		<item>
			<name>Course Catalog Links</name>
			<description>
				<line>Affected pages: Add/Edit Course Offering, Instructional Offering Detail, Instructional Offering Configuration</line>
				<line>Added a course URL provider interface (similar to the course details provider that is already used in student scheduling).
					<line>To be configured by unitime.custom.CourseUrlProvider (contains name of the class that implements the new CourseUrlProvider interface).</line>
					<line>Unlike the old interface (given by tmtbl.catalogLink.lookup.class property), a course offering does not need to exist in UniTime and it can be used for all the courses of a cross-list (not just the controlling one).</line>
					<line>PurdueCourseDetailsProvider extended to provide course URLs as well.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Add/Edit Course Offering: course catalog link changes based on the current selection of subject area and course number.</line>
				<line>Instructional Offering Detail: each course (of a cross-list) can have a course catalog link (there is a new Catalog column added in the table of courses).</line>
				<line>If the course details provider is configured as well (given by unitime.custom.CourseDetailsProvider property), course details are shown as a mouse over tooltip of a course catalog link.</line>
				<line>Clicking on the course catalog link automatically opens the course catalog in a new tab / window.</line>
				<line>Backwards compatibility: the old lookup (given by tmtbl.catalogLink.lookup.class property) can still be used.
					<line>To display catalog links, either the old tmtbl.catalogLink.lookup.class property or the new unitime.custom.CourseUrlProvider property should be configured (but not both).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Management: Event Limit</name>
			<description>
				<line>Class events: show the appropriate class limit (instead of what is set on the event itself).</line>
				<line>Examination events: show the appropriate examination size (instead of what is set on the event itself).</line>
				<line>Course-related events: show the sum of the limits of the related objects (instead of what is set on the event itself).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Notes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Edit Event: Do not create EDIT event note when there are no updated meetings and there was at least one meeting cancelled (there is also CANCEL note created).</line>
			</description>
		</item>		
	</category>
</release>	

<release>
	<version>3.4.270</version>
	<release-date>Fri, 2 Aug 2013</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Bug Fixes</title>
		<item>
			<name>Add / Edit Time Pattern</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added validation for break time. Empty break time is taken as zero number of minutes. Fixes issue 10.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Timetabling: Student Course Demands</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed ORA-00904 when Student Course Requests are being loaded as student course demands with Committed student conflicts set to Compute.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Edit Solver Configuration</name>
			<description>
				<line>Use the new GWT-based time preference grid for Time Preferences parameter.</line>
				<line>This fixes the issue introduced in revision 3863 (the old grid was displayed with 5 minute long increments).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>3.4.269</version>
	<release-date>Thu, 1 Aug 2013</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Technology Update</title>
		<item>
			<name>Event Management</name>
			<description>
				<line>Event management portion of the application was completely rewritten using Google Web Toolkit.</line>
				<line>All the existing (UniTime 3.3) functionality has remained, a number of new features was implemented (see below).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Spring Security</name>
			<description>
				<line>New security model is introduced in UniTime 3.4</line>
				<line>This includes both user authentication and authorization.</line>
				<line>This allows for better integration of UniTime 3.4 with other systems at a university.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Maven Builds</name>
			<description>
				<line>UniTime application can now be built using either Apache Ant or Maven.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Event Management</title>
		<item>
			<name>Organizational / Database Changes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Departments that can manage events (event departments) are to be specified on the Departments page.
					<line>On a department, there is a new Event Management flag.</line>
				</line>
				<line>There is a new relation between rooms (including non-university locations) and event departments.
					<line>On the Edit Room page, a room that is to have event management enabled must have an event department selected.</line>
				</line>
				<line>During the upgrade (first deployment of UniTime 3.4), the relations are automatically populated using the UniTime 3.3 way. That is:
					<line>An event department is a department that has a manager with an Event Manager role.</line>
					<line>Room is enabled for events if it is controlled by an event department.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Approval Workflow Changes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Requested meeting is in a pending state.
					<line>A requested meeting is approved automatically when requested by an event manager with the Event Location Approve permission if in a room of the event department of the manager.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Pending meeting can be approved, rejected (Event Meeting Approve permission), cancelled (Event Meeting Cancel permission), or inquired (Event Meeting Inquire permission) by an event manager.</line>
				<line>Pending meeting can be deleted (Event Meeting Delete permission) or cancelled (Event Meeting Cancel permission) by the requester or an event manager. </line>
				<line>Approved meeting cannot be deleted or rejected, it can only be cancelled (by the requester or an event manager).</line>
				<line>Cancelled and rejected meetings are kept in the database, but their status can no longer be changed.
					<line>Deleted meetings are also deleted from the database.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Cancelled and rejected meetings are only visible on the Event Detail and Edit Event page, and on the Events page with the following Event Filter settings:
					<line>Mode: Cancelled / Rejected</line>
					<line>Mode: My Events</line>
					<line>Requested By: ...</line>
				</line>
				<line>Meetings in the past can be requested or deleted only with the Event Edit Past permission. They can be approved, rejected, or cancelled only with the Event Approve Past permission.</line>
				<line>Events in a room that is not managed in UniTime (it does not have an event department defined) can be only requested by a user with permission Event Any Location.</line>
				<line>Rooms can be overbooked only by a user with the Event Location Overbook permission (for an event manager the room also has to be from the appropriate event department).</line>
				<line>Special events can be requested by someone with Event Add Special permission, course related events by Event Add Course Related and unavailabilities by Event Add Unavailable.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Status</name>
			<description>
				<line>An event management can be enabled or disabled per department and room type, using the Event Statuses page.</line>
				<line>Only departments that have event management enabled (Departments page) and room types that have at least one event room (Event Department under Edit Room page) are visible (can be enabled for event management).</line>
				<line>One of the following status can be set:
					<line>No Event Management
						<line>Event management is disabled.</line>
					</line>
					<line>Authenticated Users Can Request Events Managers Can Approve
						<line>Any authenticated user (with the appropriate right) can request an event, event managers are allowed to approve an event.</line>
					</line>
					<line>Departmental Users Can Request Events Managers Can Approve
						<line>Any instructor or timetable manager (with the appropriate right) can request an event in a room of her/his department(s), event managers are allowed to approve an event.</line>
					</line>
					<line>Event Managers Can Request Events Managers Can Approve
						<line>Only event managers are allowed to request and to approve an event.</line>
					</line>
					<line>Authenticated Users Can Request Events No Approval
						<line>Any authenticated user (with the appropriate right) can request an event, event managers are not allowed to approve an event.</line>
					</line>
					<line>Departmental Users Can Request Events No Approval
						<line>Any instructor or timetable manager (with the appropriate right) can request an event in a room of her/his department(s), event managers are not allowed to approve an event.</line>
					</line>
					<line>Event Managers Can Request Events No Approval
						<line>Only event managers are allowed to request an event, event managers are not allowed to approve an event.</line>
					</line>
				</line>
				<line>Together with an event status, a message (that is to be displayed next to the requested room of the appropriate department and room type) and a default break time can be defined.
					<line>A message is displayed as an error (room not available), if the user is not allowed to request a meeting in the room.</line>
					<line>A message is displayed as a warning, if the user is allowed to request a meeting in the room.</line>
					<line>Default break time is used as an offset between published and allocated time of an event (e.g., 10 means that the published end time of an event is 10 minutes earlier than the allocated time).</line>
				</line>
				<line>Event status, message and break time can be overridden on an individual room (Edit Room page).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Attachments</name>
			<description>
				<line>A file can be attached to an event (or a list of meetings) during its approval (approve / inquire / cancel / reject) as well as on the Add / Edit Event page (during creation or update of an event).</line>
				<line>An attached file gets included in the appropriate event email, but it is also persisted (within event notes) and can be accessed from the Event Detail page.
					<line>Only people that can access the detail page can get to the attached file.</line>
				</line>
				<line>This allows the approval process to be extended with the ability to attach a filled form with the request of an event.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Pages</name>
			<description>
				<line>Events page now contains all the filtering and display functionality that is needed for users to be able to see, request, and approve events.</line>
				<line>In the Timetable view, events are equally spaced (to see how much each time is used).
					<line>For room/personal timetable (when there is no or very unlikely overlap between events), events also shift into proper week/room.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Selection of time: allow selection of time from a drop down (15 or 30 minute increments) as well as type in (5 minute increments).</line>
				<line>Room filter: free text box, with a drop down with selections for features / groups / types, also allow for boolean queries.
					<line>For each selection, number of matching rooms is also provided.</line>
					<line>Room suggestions are also displayed.</line>
					<line>All the filtering capabilities are reachable via suggestions by just typing in (with no mouse clicking).</line>
				</line>
				<line>Event filter: combines event name, type and display mode into a similar component as the Room filter.</line>
				<line>Functionality of Events, Meetings, Add Event, and Room Availability is merged into one page.
					<line>This allows for easy swapping between different views.</line>
				</line>
				<line>The Timetable, List of Events, and List of Meetings can be easily filtered by a room or a week or weeks.</line>
				<line>Event page defaults to "My Events" (events requested by me) in "Event" rooms (rooms with event management enabled),
					changes in the filters are remembered in browser (session) cookies.
					<line>But it is possible to see (and query) class / examination events in all the rooms.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Users are able to see (and change) event meeting offsets (setup and teardown time).
					<line>Published Time: the "official" starting and end time of a meeting.</line>
					<line>Allocated Time: the time during which the room is blocked (start - setup, end + teardown)</line>
					<line>Setup Time: the offset (positive number in minutes) between allocated start time and published start time</line>
					<line>Teardown Time: the offset (positive number in minutes) between published end time and allocated end time</line>
				</line>
				<line>An event can now have additional contacts entered (not just a set of emails).</line>
				<line>It is now possible for the event to get automatically approved when it is entered by an event manager or an administrator.
					<line>Only for meetings that the user has permission to approve.</line>
					<line>When "Event Location Approve" permission is enabled for the user.</line>
				</line>
				<line>It is now possible to make multiple changes (e.g., drop a couple of meetings and add some now ones) within the Edit Event page.
					<line>Changes are only persisted (and the email notification is sent) at the end (when Save button is pressed).</line>
				</line>
				<line>It is now possible to approve / reject / inquire on multiple events at once, directly from the List of Events or List of Meetings.</line>
				<line>There is a toggle that allows an event manager or an administrator to make changes to an event (including approval) without sending a confirmation email.</line>
				<line>Event Detail page of examination, class, and course-related events shows the list of enrolled students, and their conflicts with the event (if there are any).
					<line>A meeting of a course-related event only shows as a student conflict when it is approved and the event requires students to attend.</line>
				</line>
				<line>People from additional contacts of an event can access the Event Detail page, but they cannot make any changes.
					<line>Course coordinators and instructors can access Event Detail page of class and examination events they are assigned to.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Class and examination events can be edited through the event interface (only users with the Event Edit Class or Event Edit Exam permission accordingly).</line>
				<line>Added ability to modify an existing meeting (or meetings).
					<line>On the Edit Event page, to modify a meeting, click on a (pending or approved) meeting or select one or more meetings (with the same start and end time) and use the "Modify..." action.</line>
					<line>The same dialog as with adding new meetings is used, but the information from the selected meeting (or meetings) is used to populate all the fields (including the room selection on the next page).</line>
					<line>When a different start/end time, date(s), or room(s) are selected a new meeting (or meetings) is created and the old meeting is deleted or cancelled (if it cannot be deleted).
						<line>The status of the new meeting is pending regardless the status of the old meeting.</line>
					</line>
					<line>Only meetings that can be deleted and/or cancelled can be modified as the operation always results in deleting / canceling the old meetings and creating new meetings.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Timetable Page</name>
			<description>
				<line>Event Timetable page now contains much of the Events page, but it does not have the "My Events" default and it allows to see
					<line>Room Timetable: timetable of a room</line>
					<line>Subject Timetable: timetable of a subject area or a course</line>
					<line>Curriculum Timetable: timetable of a curriculum or a curriculum classification</line>
					<line>Department Timetable: timetable of a department.</line>
					<line>Personal Timetable: timetable of a person, listing all classes, exams, and other requested events.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Room Availability</name>
			<description>
				<line>Not Available event type added.
					<line>Only event manager and administrator can create (Event Add Unavailable permission), no approval process.</line>
					<line>Not available events only show up in the timetable grid when showing a timetable of a room (or rooms), and they display differently than ordinary events (grayed out and without a shade).</line>
					<line>Not available events only show up in the events or meetings if the Not Available type is explicitly selected in the event filter, or when they are shown on the timetable grid.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Event Room Availability
					<line>Default event room availability can be edited on a room (Edit Event Availability on Room Details page).</line>
					<line>This is a semester-wide availability table very much like the one for course timetabling (Room Availability).</line>
					<line>It can be seen with Room Detail Event Availability permission, changed with Room Edit Event Availability permission.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructor (Event) Roles</name>
			<description>
				<line>A (departmental) instructor can have an additional role assigned in UniTime, using Instructor Roles page.
					<line>Only roles that are made available to instructors (Instructor toggle on the Roles page) can be used.</line>
					<line>The page is only available when there is at least one role available to instructors.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Intended use case: event manager can assign people of his/her department with some lesser event roles (e.g., to be able to request course-related events, approve events, ...)
					<line>An instructor with an event role will be able to request an event while the event status is one of the following:
						<line>Authenticated Users Can Request</line>
						<line>Departmental Users Can Request</line>
						<line>Event Managers Can Request</line>
					</line>
					<line>An instructor with an event role that allows him / her to approve will be able to approve (or reject) an event while the event status allows for event managers to approve events.</line>
					<line>In both cases, department of the instructor is considered (and compared with event department of the room in question).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Class Assignment, Solution Commit / Uncommit</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability not to change the past meetings when a class assignment is changed.
					<line>When application property tmtbl.classAssign.changePastMeetings is set to false (defaults to true).</line>
					<line>When an event is changed, a note (with a description, user, time stamp etc.) is added to the meeting.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Localization</name>
			<description>
				<line>All event management pages are fully localizable.</line>
				<line>English and Czech translations are provided.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Accessibility</name>
			<description>
				<line>All event pages are made accessible (and screen reader friendly) using WAI-ARIA standard.
					<line>See http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria and https://developers.google.com/web-toolkit/doc/latest/DevGuideA11y for more details.</line>
				</line>
				<line>All event pages are made accessible using the WAI ARIA standard.</line>
				<line>FireFox with NVDA provides the best user experience.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Deprecated Pages</name>
			<description>
				<line>Meetings and Room Availability pages are no longer needed -- all the functionality is available on the new Events page.</line>
				<line>Classes, Examination, Personal schedule pages are no longer needed -- all the functionality is available on the new Event Timetable page.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Application Security</title>
		<item>
			<name>User Permissions</name>
			<description>
				<line>Roles and their permissions can now be edited in UniTime which greatly improves customization possibilities.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>System Administrator</name>
			<description>
				<line>The current Administrator role has been renamed to System Administrator role.</line>
				<line>New Session Administrator role has been introduced.
					<line>Very much like the System Administrator, but academic session dependent.</line>
					<line>Only system administrator is able to create and / or delete an academic session.</line>
					<line>Session independent entities (like room types) are only editable by system administrator.</line>
					<line>Chameleon is only available to a system administrator by default.
						<line>If chameleon permission is given to (session) administrator, he/she cannot chameleon into a system administrator role (or any other role that is session independent).</line>
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Improved Application Security</name>
			<description>
				<line>For instance, a course timetabling solution can only be uncommitted when the online student scheduling is NOT enabled.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Alternative Date Patterns</name>
			<description>
				<line>User interface for alternative date patterns created.
					<line>A date pattern can be of a new type "Alternative Pattern Set"</line>
					<line>Such a date pattern does not have any dates selected by itself, but other date patterns can be put into this set (one date pattern can belong into multiple sets).</line>
				</line>
				<line>When such a date pattern is assigned to a scheduling subpart or a class, one of the date patterns of the set are to be assigned to the class as a part of the time assignment.
					<line>An individual preference can be set on each of the alternative date patterns (including required and prohibited).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Travel Times</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to override distances computed using room coordinates by individual travel times set between pairs of rooms.
					<line>These, if set, override the default distances that are computed using room coordinates.</line> 
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Back-To-Back Student Distance Conflicts</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to consider student distance conflicts between classes that are not directly back-to-back.
					<line>Distance conflict is there if room distance (in minutes) is greater than the break time of the first class plus the difference between end of the first and start of the second class.</line>
					<line>To be enabled if needed by setting the solver parameter Distances.ComputeDistanceConflictsBetweenNonBTBClasses to true (defaults to false).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Back-To-Back Instructor Distance Conflicts</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Added ability to check travel times between classes that are not back-to-back (there is one or more empty slots in between).
					<line>A hard conflict is created between two consecutive classes that do not have enough time to travel.
						<line>Like with student conflicts, travel time in minutes is compared with the break time of the first class and the time between the classes.</line>
					</line>
					<line>Discouraged (soft) conflict is created if there is not enough time to travel while the break time of the first class is ignored (i.e., when break time has to be used for travel, not to wrap up the class).</line>
					<line>Strongly discouraged (soft) conflict is created for two consecutive classes that are too far away (regardless the available time in between).
						<line>This means that there is a strongly discouraged conflict every time when an instructor has a long travel time between two classes during the day.</line>
						<line>This is controlled by Instructor.InstructorLongTravelInMinutes solver parameter, defaults to 30 minutes (instructor has to travel for 30 minutes or more).</line>
						<line>This allows us to minimize long (instructor) travels during the day.</line>
					</line>
					<line>To be enabled if needed by setting the solver parameter Distances.ComputeDistanceConflictsBetweenNonBTBClasses to true (defaults to false).</line>
					<line>The distance check between back-to-back classes remains as before (the change only applies to non back-to-back consecutive classes, when enabled).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Automatic Precedence Constraints</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Added ability to automatically post a precedence constraint between a class and all its parent classes.
					<line>To be enabled by setting the solver parameter General.AutoPrecedence (value is the preference of the constraint, e.g., R for required, -2 for strongly preferred).</line>
					<line>Classes have to be of different instructional types (a constraint will not be created between Lec and Lec a).</line>
					<line>This is to allow lecture before seminar scenario without manually creating a lot of precedence constraints.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Hard Conflicts</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability for the joint enrollment constraint (student conflicts) to be hard based on the number of students in common.</line>
				<line>This is controlled by the parameter General.JenrlMaxConflicts, the value is the percentage of the smaller class (using class limits) which gives the limit on the join enrollment (number of students in common) to become hard. Examples:
					<line>1.0 means the constraint is always soft (default)</line>
					<line>0.0 means the constraint is always hard</line>
					<line>0.25 means that a join enrollment constraint will be hard if there is at least 25% students of the smaller class in common</line>
					<line>So, for instance if there are two classes of limit 20, with the value 0.25 these classes can conflict only if there are 5 or less students attending both classes.</line>
				</line>
				<line>A hard conflict can weaken over time using the WeakeningConstraint interface.
					<line>With each unassignment caused by the constraint, the max conflicts parameter is increased by General.JenrlMaxConflictsWeaken parameter (defaults to 0.001).</line>
				</line>
				<line>Hard conflicts can be created only between classes that are not committed (otherwise there is a risk of not being able to assign a class in time because of committed conflicts).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Date Mapping</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to create a mapping of class dates to event dates (list of pairs class date → event date related to an academic session).</line>
				<line>When a mapping is defined, it is used for creation of class events (class dates are mapped to event dates) and for room availability in course timetabling (events are mapped back from event dates to class dates).</line>
				<line>The mapping can be defined on Administration > Academic Sessions > Event Date Mappings page.
					<line>The existing mappings can be seen with Event Date Mappings permission (if there is any) and edited with the Event Date Mapping Edit permission (no timetable cannot be committed at that time).</line>
					<line>These two permissions are not assigned to any role by default, making this feature not visible by default.</line>
				</line>
				<line>When a date mapping is defined, the date patterns should be defined so that classes do take place on the class dates (marked with purple text color in the pattern) and not on the event dates (marked with teal color in the pattern).
					<line>Such meetings will be mapped from these class dates to the event dates using the defined mapping when a solution is committed (or a committed assignment is changed using Class Assignment page).</line>
				</line>
				<line>The mapping does not roll forward.</line>
				<line>Use Case: Rare timetabling exceptions usually caused by following a different day schedule on a certain dates (e.g., because there is too many Monday holidays in the term).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Ignore Student Conflicts Constraint</name>
			<description>
				<line>A new distribution constraint Ignore Student Conflicts was created.
					<line>If put (with Required preference) on a set of classes, all student conflicts are ignored between these classes.</line>
					<line>It is ignored when Neutral preference is used (it only allows for Required or Neutral preference).</line>
				</line>
				<line>The Same Students distribution constraint allows for classes that are also connected with a required Ignore Student Conflicts distribution constraint to be put on top of each other or back-to-back too far apart.</line>
				<line>If the number of student conflicts that are being ignored is to be displayed in the solution info, the following two classes need to be added to General.AdditionalCriteria solver parameter:
					<line>General.AdditionalCriteria=net.sf.cpsolver.coursett.criteria.additional.IgnoredStudentConflict;net.sf.cpsolver.coursett.criteria.additional.IgnoredCommittedStudentConflict</line>   
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Enabled for Student Scheduling</name>
			<description>
				<line>The "Display In Schedule Book" toggle (that can be set on a class) changed to (enabled for) "Student Scheduling" toggle.
					<line>The display in schedule book toggle had no meaning in UniTime, the setting was only recorded.</line>
					<line>Now, if a class is disabled for student scheduling it appears in student scheduling (both batch and online) as if it had zero limit.</line>
					<line>This means, that the class does not show up in the Course Finder dialog, and a student can get in the class only if he/she has an individual reservation for the class.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Added flexible group constraints</name>
			<description>
				<line>Flexible constraint expresses relations between several classes.
					<line>It provides similar functions as group constraint, but it is able to take additional parameters from its reference field.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added two new flexible group constraints:
					<line>Break constraint checks for instructor lunch break or a break in general in between the given classes.
						<line>It has three parameters: a start and an end time of a window in which the break is required / preferred, and a minimal length of a break that is needed.</line>
						<line>Reference _Break:132:162:30_ translates to a break of at least 30 minutes between 11 am (slot 132) and 1:30 pm (slot 162).</line>
					</line>
					<line>MaxBlock constraint checks for too big blocks of back-to-back classes of an instructor.
						<line>It has two parameters: a maximal length of a back-to-back block that is allowed and a minimal length of a break between two classes not to be considered in the same block.</line>
						<line>Reference _MaxBlock:120:30_ translates to a maximal block of at most 2 hours (120 minutes) with classes not more than 30 minutes a part.</line>
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offering Detail: Make Not Offered</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to stay on the detail page when the offering is made not offered.
					<line>Controlled by the application property unitime.offering.makeNotOfferedStaysOnDetail (defaults to false -- current behavior).</line>
					<line>When going back to the Instructional Offerings page, scroll down to the offering that has been made not offered.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Add Course Offering</name>
			<description>
				<line>On the Instructional Offerings page, Add New button does not create the course offering right away but it leads to a new page Add Course Offering.</line>
				<line>A new offering is only created when the page is saved (there is no database change when Back button is clicked).</line>
				<line>Subject area and course number can be entered on the Instructional Offerings page or on the Add Course Offering page.</line>
				<line>Same items as on the Edit Course Offering page (for a controlling course offering) can be entered.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Curriculum Timetabling</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to display course registrations (student course requests) together with last-like and enrollment data.</line>
				<line>Curriculum table: selected counter columns can be hidden (selection is memorized in the cookie).</line>
				<line>Classifications: lines with no counts are automatically hidden (e.g., if there are no last-like course demands, last-like and projected counts will not be displayed).</line>
				<line>Curricula section (of an offering detail): modes that have no data are not available (e.g., if there are no last-like course demands, last-like numbers cannot be displayed).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Course Demands: Curriculum Course Requests</name>
			<description>
				<line>It is now possible to combine curricula with pre-registration data (student course requests).</line>
				<line>To enable, set Student Course Demands solver parameter to Curricula Requests Course Demands (this option may need to be added in the parameter).
					<line>When there are 50% or more students in a curriculum already registered, the curriculum model pretty much copies the pre-registration data.</line>
					<line>When there are less students pre-registered: the pre-registrations are completed with made-up students (following the curriculum).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructor Student Conflicts</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to link students with instructors (e.g., based on their external unique id).</line>
				<line>There is an instructor student conflict if an instructor (of a class) is also enrolled as a student into some other class and the two classes are overlapping in time or are back-to-back in rooms that are too far apart.</line>
				<line>The instructor student conflicts can be enabled by setting the solver configuration property Global.LoadStudentInstructorConflicts to true.
					<line>These should be only enabled when student course requests or the actual student class enrollments are used as student course demands.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Instructor student conflicts can be weighted more than plain student conflicts using the weight Comparator.InstructorStudentConflictWeight.</line>
				<line>Instructor student conflicts are marked by word "instructor" in the listing and on the Solver Reports page.</line>
				<line>When showing instructor schedules on Timetable page and the solution is loaded in memory:
					<line>Student class enrollment are included in the instructor's schedule (class name in italics).</line>
					<line>When background is set to student conflicts: conflicting classes (for the instructor) have blue background</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Examination Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Can Share Room</name>
			<description>
				<line>Can Share Room distribution constraint was added.
					<line>Given examinations can share a room (use the same room during the same period) if the room is big enough.</line>
					<line>If examinations of different seating type are sharing a room, the more restrictive seating type is used to check the room size.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Examination Types</name>
			<description>
				<line>Allow for multiple final/midterm examination types in one academic session.
					<line>Examination types are now editable within the application.</line>
					<line>Only examination types that have examination periods defined are visible within an academic session.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Room Size Penalty</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to make the difference function polynomial with a new parameter Exams.RoomSizeFactor (defaults to 1.0).</line>
				<line>New objective value: (room size - number of students) ^ room size factor.</line>
				<line>This is to be able to favor a room swap between two exams at the same period, in which a smaller exam takes a smaller room.
					<line>To do this, set Exams.RoomSizeFactor to a number bigger than one that is close to one (e.g., 1.05).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Distance To A Strongly Preferred Room</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added an experimental criterion measuring average distance (in meters) to the strongly preferred room (or rooms) of the examination.</line>
				<line>The idea is to prefer rooms that are close to the strongly preference room (if there is a strongly preferred room but it is not available).</line>
				<line>A weight of the average distance between the assigned room(s) and the strongly preferred room or rooms can be set using Exams.DistanceToStronglyPreferredRoomWeight property.</line>
				<line>To enable this criterion add the DistanceToStronglyPreferredRoom class name to Exams.AdditionalCriteria parameter. For instance:
					<line>Exams.AdditionalCriteria=net.sf.cpsolver.exam.criteria.additional.DistanceToStronglyPreferredRoom</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Room Placement Penalty</name>
			<description>
				<line>Combination of examination room preference (set on an exam) and room period preference (set on a room) changed.</line>
				<line>Now it is 2x examination room preference PLUS room period preference of the examination period in question.
					<line>Was: examination room preference if it was set (there was a room, building,
						group, or feature containing the room set on the exam itself); room period
						preference otherwise (if there is no examination room preference).</line>
				</line>
				<line>This is to be able to distinguish between a preferred room that has no period preference and a preferred room that is discouraged at the given period.
					<line>While the preferences set on the exam have still higher weights than the period preferences set on the room.</line>
					<line>Except when the period is prohibited in which case the room cannot be used at that period at all (this did not change).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Period Placement Penalty</name>
			<description>
				<line>Period placement penalty is now counted in the same way as the room placement penalty, that is: 2 * exam period penalty + default period penalty
					<line>where "exam period penalty" is the penalty set on the exam and "default period penalty" is the (default) penalty set on the period.</line>
				</line>
				<line>This way a preference on an exam does not get negated with a preference on the period (e.g., strongly preferring a period that is strongly discouraged does not result in zero penalty).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Examination Roll Forward</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to
					<line>not roll forward any examination preferences, or</line>
					<line>roll forward all examination preferences.</line>
					The default is still to roll forward only building, room feature and room group preferences (excluding period and room preferences).
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Examination Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>Examination detail page now contains an Enrollment table. This table lists all students enrolled in the exam, including their conflicts.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Solution XML Export</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to export solution XML (by default available only to administrators, permissions Examination Solution Export Xml and Student Sectioning Solution Export Xml).</line>
				<line>This is the format that is used directly by the solver, see http://www.unitime.org/exam_datasets.php</line>
				<line>By default, exported XMLs do not have any names or external IDs, only UniTime unique IDs; this can be changed by the following two application properties:
					<line>unitime.solution.export.names (if true names are included, defaults to false)</line>
					<line>unitime.solution.export.id-conv (if true UniTime unique IDs are serialized, defaults to false)</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Batch Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Ignore Student Conflicts Constraint</name>
			<description>
				<line>It is now allowed for a student to be enrolled in conflicting classes (overlapping in time or back-to-back too far a part) if there is a required Ignore Student Conflicts between them.
					<line>Such a conflict is completely ignored (e.g., unlike with classes that allow for overlap, it does not try to minimize the overlapping time).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Sectioning Status (No Batch option)</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to exclude some students from batch student scheduling.
					<line>Students with sectioning status that has "No Batch" option checked are not loaded into the solver.</line>
					<line>If these students already enrolled into some classes, they enrollments are counted towards the class, configuration, course, and reservation limits.
						<line>Internally, the appropriate limits (if not unlimited) are decreased by the number of students that are enrolled in and not being scheduled by the solver (during the data load).</line>
					</line>
					<line>This behavior is enabled by default, it can be switched off by setting the solver parameter Load.CheckForNoBatchStatus to false.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added ability to set or reset student status (for the students that have been loaded into the solver) while a solution is being saved.
					<line>This is done by solver parameter Save.StudentSectioningStatusToSet, that can have the following parameters (e.g., defined as an enum):
						<line>N/A ... student status is kept as it is</line>
						<line>Default ... student status is set to null (the status of a student is given by the default status on the academic session)</line>
						<line>An abbreviation of the status (from Student Scheduling Status Types page) that is to be set to each student which has been loaded into the solver during the save.</line>
					</line>
					<line>If the parameter is not present (which is the default), student statuses are kept as they are during the save.</line> 
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Solution XML Export</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to export solution XML (by default available only to administrators, permissions Examination Solution Export Xml and Student Sectioning Solution Export Xml).</line>
				<line>This is the format that is used directly by the solver, see http://www.unitime.org/sct_datasets.php</line>
				<line>By default, exported XMLs do not have any names or external IDs, only UniTime unique IDs; this can be changed by the following two application properties:
					<line>unitime.solution.export.names (if true names are included, defaults to false)</line>
					<line>unitime.solution.export.id-conv (if true UniTime unique IDs are serialized, defaults to false)</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Online Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Course Types</name>
			<description>
				<line>Course types can be defined under Administration &gt; Other &gt; Course Types</line>
				<line>Each course offering can have a course type (to be edited on Edit Course Offering page).</line>
				<line>Through student scheduling status types, a student can be allowed to request only courses of certain course types.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Consent Types</name>
			<description>
				<line>Consent of department / instructor moved from instructional offering to course offering level.</line>
				<line>This (together with course reservations) allows for the use case when a consent is only needed for students that enroll into the offering through one of the cross-listed courses.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Ignore Student Conflicts Constraint</name>
			<description>
				<line>It is now allowed for a student to be enrolled in conflicting classes (overlapping in time or back-to-back too far a part) if there is a required Ignore Student Conflicts between them.
					<line>Such a conflict is completely ignored (e.g., the two classes are not marked as conflicting in the Student Scheduling Assistant).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Wait-listing</name>
			<description>
				<line>Introduced ability to enable/disable wait-listing for a course request.
					<line>This is created according to the original design (wait-list toggle is a part of course request data entry; there will likely be some changes and refinements).</line>
					<line>It does not apply to scheduling assistant mode (no wait-list toggles there, only for collecting course requests and for full online scheduling).</line>
					<line>There is a new toggle on a Student Scheduling Status Type enabling / disabling wait-listing that can be used to disable wait-listing for a particular student or on an academic session as default.</line>
				</line>
				<line>While this approach is compatible with the original design and with the inner workings of the solver, it changes how the wait-listing is done.
					<line>Before this change, computation of a student schedule behaved as with no wait-listing enabled (any unassigned request could get an alternative request assigned instead); but every unassigned request was automatically wait-listed.</line>
					<line>Now, if a course request is wait-listed, a student cannot get an alternative course.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Accessibility</name>
			<description>
				<line>The Student Scheduling Assistant page is made accessible (and screen reader friendly) using WAI-ARIA standard.
					<line>See http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria and https://developers.google.com/web-toolkit/doc/latest/DevGuideA11y for more details.</line>
				</line>
				<line>FireFox with NVDA provides the best user experience.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Other Changes</title>
		<item>
			<name>Rooms</name>
			<description>
				<line>Room availability grid rewritten in GWT.
					<line>Department code is displayed in each cell.</line>
					<line>It is now much easier to add / remove a department, add all departments.</line>
					<line>Localization (e.g., times / dates follow the locale settings)</line>
					<line>User interface is customizable, however, a lot of code still expects half hours starting on every half an hour.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Room Feature Types</name>
			<description>
				<line>Room features can have a type (optional, to be defined on the page Administration > Other > Room Feature Types).
					<line>Room feature type can be enabled or disabled for event management, room features of a disabled feature type are not available in event management (Room Filter box).</line>
					<line>Rooms Features: if there are room feature types defined, each room feature (global or departmental) can have none (No Type) or one feature type assigned.</line>
					<line>Room feature preferences: feature type abbreviation is added to the room feature name in the dropdowns (next to the feature name, in brackets).</line>
					<line>Room tooltip: features are split by room feature type, only applicable feature types are displayed.</line>
					<line>Class Assignment: room features are split by type in the Available Rooms section.</line>
					<line>Examination Assignment: room features are split by type in the Available Rooms section, only room features with at least one examination room (of the same type as the exam) are displayed.</line>
					<line>Room Filter box (event management): features are split by type in the dropdown (+), they can also be searched by feature type (features of the type that is being typed in are suggested).</line>
					<line>The same rules as before still apply -- if two room features are selected, a room has to have both to match (regardless their type).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Room Area (Square Footage)</name>
			<description>
				<line>Rooms and Non-University Locations have a new property called Area (double precision).
					<line>Room area can be edited on the Edit Room page (requires Room Edit Change Room Properties permission).</line>
					<line>It is displayed on the Room Detail and the Rooms pages, and also in the room tooltip (if present).</line>
					<line>Default units are square feet, but they can be changed through the localization.</line>
					<line>External rooms and the appropriate XML import can include room area as well.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Room Note</name>
			<description>
				<line>Rooms and Non-University Locations have a new note.
					<line>A note can be edited on the Edit Room Page.</line>
					<line>It is visible on the Room Detail page (if present), in the room tooltip, and in the events (where it overrides the note that is set on the room type &amp; department combination, Event Statuses page).</line>
					<line>A history of the room note is available on the Room Detail page (section Room Note History at the bottom of the page).
						<line>There is also a toggle allowing to display note changes across all academic sessions (rooms are matched using their permanent ids).</line>
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>		
		<item>
			<name>Room Sharing</name>
			<description>
				<line>Room Sharing Grid
					<line>Room sharing grid no longer needs to be defined in half-hour increments starting on every hour or half-hour.</line>
					<line>Default settings can be changed using unitime.room.sharingMode.X application properties (where X is a number starting from 1), or by overriding GWTConstant called roomSharingModes.</line>
					<line>Format: name|first slot|last slot|first day|last day|increment</line>
					<line>Defaults:
						<line>unitime.room.sharingMode1=Workdays × Daytime|0|4|90|222|6
							<line>Monday - Friday, starting at 7:30 am, ending at 6:30 pm, in half-hour increments</line>
						</line>
						<line>unitime.room.sharingMode2=All Week × Daytime|0|6|90|222|6
							<line>Monday - Sunday, starting at 7:30 am, ending at 6:30 pm, in half-hour increments</line>
						</line>
						<line>unitime.room.sharingMode3=Workdays × Evening|0|4|222|288|6
							<line>Monday - Friday, starting at 6:30 pm, ending at midnight, in half-hour increments</line>
						</line>
						<line>unitime.room.sharingMode4=All Week × Evening|0|5|222|288|6
							<line>Monday - Sunday, starting at 6:30 pm, ending at midnight, in half-hour increments</line>
						</line>
						<line>unitime.room.sharingMode5=All Week × All Times|0|6|0|288|6
							<line>Monday - Sunday, starting at midnight, ending at midnight, in half-hour increments</line>
						</line>
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>		
		<item>
			<name>Instructor Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>Instructor Availability (Time Preferences)
					<line>Time preferences grid no longer needs to be defined in half-hour increments starting on every hour or half-hour.</line>
					<line>Default settings can be changed using unitime.room.sharingMode.X application properties (where X is a number starting from 1), or by overriding GWTConstant called roomSharingModes.
						<line>See the Room Sharing Grid above for the format and the defaults of these properties.</line>
					</line>
					<line>To avoid time preference combinations issues, it is no longer possible to require a particular time on an instructor (all other times must be prohibited instead).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Export to PDF/CSV/XML</name>
			<description>
				<line>Instead of generating a temporary file, the PDF/CSV/XML content is exported within the HTTP servlet response.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Designators</name>
			<description>
				<line>Designators page and Designator Required toggle (on the offering) removed.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Application Configuration</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to define session dependent application properties.
					<line>This is to allow multiple campuses / colleges better co-exist in one database, or for instance to have different starting times in Summer than Spring and Fall.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Configuration Roll Forward</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to roll session configuration forward.
					<line>Session configuration contains application configuration, standard notes, event room notes, and break times that are applied directly to the session and/or its department(s).</line>
					<line>Individual room notes and break times are rolled forward with the rooms.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Reservations Roll Forward</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to roll reservations from one academic session to another.
					<line>Course, curriculum, and student group reservations can be rolled forward.</line>
					<line>For reservations with an expiration date filled in, it is possible to reset the expiration date to a given date.</line>
					<line>Each subject area and/or reservation type can be rolled forward separately.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Scripts</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to run small programs through the interface (page Administration > Utilities > Scripts).
					<line>E.g., to reset all examination preferences for a particular examination problem.</line>
					<line>It is possible to plug-in additional scripting engines (e.g., python).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Date Formatting</name>
			<description>
				<line>To prevent concurrency issues (see bug JDK-6609686, http://bugs.sun.com/view_bug.do?bug_id=4264153) and to ease localization of date formats, most of the date formating is now done through the new Formats class.
					<line>Instead of new DateFormat(pattern), the new Formats.getDateFormat(pattern) is used.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Database Authentication: Password Change</name>
			<description>
				<line>When a user is authenticated through UniTime's users table (which is the default), allow an authenticated user to change his/her password.
					<line>Menu: Preferences > Change Password</line>
				</line>
				<line>It is also possible to request a password change for a user (identified by his/her email).
					<line>Page ...UniTime/gwt.jsp?page=password&amp;reset=1</line>
					<line>The entered email must match with a timetabling manager, a staff, an instructor, or a student and there has to be an appropriate record in the users table (with a matching external unique id).</line>
					<line>If there is a match, an email is sent to the user with a generated link through which the user can change his/her password.</line>
					<line>There is a temporary key generated that can be used instead of the old email, it is valid for 48 hours.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Logging</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added page Administration > Defaults > Logging that can be used to adjust logging levels while the application is running.</line>
				<line>Logging messages can be saved in the new MessageLog table.
					<line>Messages are kept for 14 days (can be changed by custom property unitime.message.log.cleanup.days).</line>
					<line>Only messages of level warning and higher are saved (can be changed by custom property unitime.message.log.level).</line>
					<line>There is a new report Message Log under Administration > Academic Session > Reports.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Localization</name>
			<description>
				<line>All the pages that are written in GWT can be localized.
					<line>This includes online student scheduling, event management, curriculum, reservations, HQL reports, travel times, and all the new administration pages.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
</release-history>
