<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="Release-Notes.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE release-history PUBLIC "-//UniTime//UniTime Release Notes DTD/EN" "Release-Notes.dtd">
<!--
 * Licensed to The Apereo Foundation under one or more contributor license
 * agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for
 * additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 *
 * The Apereo Foundation licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
 * Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
 * compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at:
 *
 * http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 *
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 *
 -->

<release-history>
<doc-title>UniTime 4.5 Release Notes</doc-title>
<release>
	<version>4.5.${build.number}</version>
	<release-date>${build.date}</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Curriculum Reservation: Minors</name>
			<description>
				<line>Corrected computation of last-like and projected demands on curriculum reservations.</line>
				<line>Fixed an &quot;ORA-01722: invalid number&quot; error when there is a reservation with a minor and the course has some last-like demands with minors.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Event Management</title>
		<item>
			<name>Events: Avoid Duplicate Consecutive Notes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Remove duplicate consecutive notes from the display and exports.</line>
				<line>A duplicate note is created, for instance, when an automatically approved meeting is created (as there is Create and Approve action logged with the same text note).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Administration</title>
		<item>
			<name>Data Exchange: Staff XML Import</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to disable incremental mode (when incremental=&quot;false&quot; on the root element).</line>
				<line>To delete a staff member, delete element can be set to T, Y, or true (case insensitive).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Administration: Export PDF/CSV</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added an ability to export the admin table in CSV or PDF.</line>
				<line>Aplies to all 40+ admin pages using SimpleEditPage (gwt.jsp?page=admin&amp;type=XXX).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
<release>
	<version>4.5.177</version>
	<release-date>Fri, 1 Oct 2021</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Student Scheduling Reports: Tableau Report</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added Request Type column (including request priority: Critical, Important, or Normal).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Advisor Course Recommendations</name>
			<description>
				<line>When the Notes textarea is automatically resized to fit the text, avoid scroll-position jumping on Firefox.</line>
				<line>Do not cache previous notes query (this is to ensure that the most recent notes are visible).</line>
				<line>When there are no advisor course recommendations, but the page is pre-populated with student's course requests, still display the default advisor note.</line>
				<line>When pre-populating student course requests with advisor recommendations, only check true courses for duplicates (not free texts).</line>
				<line>Do not allow the same course to be entered multiple times (duplicate free texts are allowed).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Scheduling Link (UniTime/studentScheduling.do)</name>
			<description>
				<line>If an instructor role is assigned, prefer student role when possible.</line>
				<line>When selecting current authority, do not stick with the default academic session when unitime.studentScheduling.useDefaultSession = false.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Online Student Scheduling Dashboard: Student Notes</name>
			<description>
				<line>When online student scheduling is not enabled, corrected the logic of computing the last note of a student.
					<line>This fixes an issue of showing an older note instead of the last one for students with no course requests.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Solution Commit: Skip Conflict Checking</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to skip room and instructor conflict checking with other committed problems.</line>
				<line>Set unitime.commit.skipConflictChecking to true to skip the checks, defaults to false.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Class Assignment: Bugfix</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed an error that sometimes appear when a class with two or more date patterns available is being assigned (Exception thrown by getter for property times of bean model).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Examination Assignment: Not-Assigned</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added an ability to unassign an exam (remove its current assingment).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Examination Detail: Delete</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed a &quot;deleted object would be re-saved by cascade&quot; issue which sometimes appears when an assigned exam that has some student conflicts is being deleted.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Administration</title>
		<item>
			<name>Data Exchange: Student Course Requests XML Import</name>
			<description>
				<line>Improved speed of the import by pre-loading and caching available student statuses.</line>
			</description>
		</item><item>
			<name>Data Exchange: Academic Session Import</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed a potential issue with uk_student_area_clasf_major unique key.
					<line>Optional concentration is part of the index, which can cause troubles when there is a student with two or more (area,classification,major) elements that differ only in concentration.</line>
					<line>Concentration is now set together with the required fields.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>People Lookup: Adjustments</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to specify which sources will be searched and in which order.
					<line>By setting unitime.lookup.source.defaults property containing a comma separated list of sources, defaults to ldap,students,instructors,staff,managers,events,advisors.</line>
				</line>
				<line>When searching instructors, added ability to prefer instructors with the matching department code in the Staff table.
					<line>By setting unitime.lookup.instructors.checkStaffDept to true (defaults to false).</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added ability to not return emails for some roles.
					<line>By setting unitime.lookup.showEmail.&lt;role-ref&gt; to false (defaults to true, role-ref is the role reference for which Emails should be shown/hidden).</line>
					<line>Do not use for roles that can request an event on behalf of someone else.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Hide columns Email or Phone when there is no match with an email or phone filled in respectively.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Documentation</title>
		<item>
			<name>UniTime 4.5 Online Help</name>
			<description>
				<line>Use https://help45.unitime.org for the online help.</line>
				<line>Starting with this release of UniTime 4.5, the online help has been moved to the new Google Sites (from the classic Google Sites).
					<line>URL formatting has changed (e.g., Instructional Offerings > https://help45.unitime.org/instructional-offerings).</line>
					<line>The help page can no longer be opened in a frame (it now opens in a new tab).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
<release>
	<version>4.5.164</version>
	<release-date>Sat, 24 Apr 2021</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Online Student Scheduling Dashboard: Student Notes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Show all students notes in a new Notes tab when a student is clicked, including time stamp and the name of the user who set the note.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Advisor Course Recommendations: Custom Warnings</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added the same warnings that the student would see using the custom course validation provider.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Advisor Course Recommendations: Read-Only Use</name>
			<description>
				<line>A few small improvements for users with read-only access to the Advisor Course Recommendations page.
					<line>Show student status and PIN correctly (with the PIN toggle disabled).</line>
					<line>Degree Plan button works without the Student Advisor permission (Advisor Course Request permission works as well).</line>
					<line>Advisor Course Recommendations appears in the menu even when there is no Students menu.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Requests Validation: Free Times</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added a warning message when free time is requested (regardless of its priority)
					<line>The Free Time request will be considered a time block during the preregistration process.
  						If the Free Time request is placed higher than a traditional course, you may not receive a full schedule.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Also added a warning on a free time request that is above a course
					<line>High priority free time</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Online Student Scheduling Dashboard: Change Log</name>
			<description>
				<line>A few changes have been made to make the Change Log load faster, namely
					<line>Only parse the action proto message when an item is clicked.</line>
					<line>Message field updated to contain a message generated from the action so that the same message gets shown on the dashboard without the needed to parse the action proto.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Batch Student Scheduling: Backtracking phase</name>
			<description>
				<line>Ensure that the solver does not get stuck (as it repeatedly adds requests that failed) by setting a limit on the number of iterations (2x the initial size of the request queue).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Event Management</title>
		<item>
			<name>Event Detail: Email Students</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to email students of a class, an examination or a course related event.</line>
				<line>Requires permission Event Detail Email Students (not enabled by default).
					<line>When enabled, Send Email button appears on the top of the Enrollments table.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Either all students that have an email on file can be emailed, or just those that are selected.</line>
				<line>One email is sent with all the (selected) students in BCC.</line>
				<line>CC defaults to the user's email, but it can be changed in the Send email dialog.</line>
				<line>Email subject defaults to the event's name, but it can be changed in the Send email dialog.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Event Timetable: Curriculum</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed an issue caused by a recent changes in curriculum reservations (curriculum reservation can now list multiple academic areas).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Other</title>
		<item>
			<name>CSV Files</name>
			<description>
				<line>When reading CSV file, consider line breaks inside of cells -- do not import as multiple lines.</line>
				<line>This fixes an issue with the validation and enrollment logs on the Student Sectioning Solver Reports page (the table gets disordered after a student with multiple curricula).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Spring libraries updated due to security issues</name>
			<description>
				<line>Spring core libraries updated to version 4.3.30 (was 4.3.18) to fix CVE-2018-15756 issue (high severity).</line>
				<line>Spring integration is updated to version 4.3.24 (was 4.3.18) to fix CVE-2020-5413 issue (high severity).</line>
				<line>Spring security is updated to version 4.2.20 (was 4.2.9) to fix CVE-2020-5408, CVE-2019-11272, and CVE-2019-3795 issues (moderate to high severities).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
<release>
	<version>4.5.154</version>
	<release-date>Wed, 17 Mar 2021</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Student Academic Area Classification Major Weight</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to add a weight to each (area, classification, major) combination that a student has.</line>
				<line>It defaults to 1.0 and can be used to avoid double counting a student with two or more majors.</line>
				<line>Added optional weight parameter in Students XML and Student Course Requests XML import and export.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Timetabling Solver: Student Course Demands</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed an issue where a first-choice course is marked as alternative to each other, making the solver to ignore student conflicts within the course.
					<line>This was only a problem when student course demands are used and alternatives are enabled (StudentCourseRequests.IncludeAlternatives is true).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Timetabling Solver: Automatic Same Students Constraint</name>
			<description>
				<line>When creating a same student constraint, consider all subparts that have just one class (not just those that do not have a parent).</line>
				<line>This fixes an issue when there is Lec 1 - Lec 1a chain and Lab 1 - Lab 1a chain which are not in a parent-child relation.
					<line>Before, only constraints between Lec 1 - Lec 1a - Lab 1 and Lab 1 - Lab 1a - Lec 1 were created, allowing Lec 1a to overlap with Lab 1a.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Class Assignment: Projected Student Conflicts</name>
			<description>
				<line>When student conflict pre-fetching is enabled (tmtbl.classAssign.prefetchConflicts),
					ensure that only committed classes from the current academic session are considered.</line>
				<line>This fixes an issue when a combination of last-like and real students are being used
					(e.g., Course Requests With Projected Last Likes) as the pre-fetch was getting conflict
					between the current and the last-like session.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Distribution Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to export the distribution preferences in CSV format.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Advisor Course Recommendations: Last Additional Notes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to select from the previous 50 notes that the advisor has used in the given term.
					<line>Student PIN is automatically replaced (same message with different PIN does not list multiple times).</line>
					<line>Ordered by the last time the note was used.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Scheduling Dashboards (Both Online and Batch)</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added optional Conc (major concentration) and Degr (student degree) columns.</line>
				<line>Added ability to filter by concentration and/or degree.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Examination Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Examination Distribution Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to export the distribution preferences in CSV format.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Other</title>
		<item>
			<name>UniTime Login Page</name>
			<description>
				<line>Include global info/warn/error messages on the UniTime login screen.
					<line>Properties tmtbl.global.info, tmtbl.global.warn, and tmtbl.global.error</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added ability to add info/warn/error messages just on the login screen.
					<line>Properties tmtbl.page.info.login, tmtbl.page.warn.login, tmtbl.page.error.login</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Curriculum Information</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to include an optional concentration and degree field on a student, with academic area, major, and classification.</line>
				<line>Included in Student XML and Course Requests XML exports and imports.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
<release>
	<version>4.5.141</version>
	<release-date>Tue, 9 Feb 2021</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Batch Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Past Sections</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to mark sections that are in the past, that is sections that start before the General.ClassesPastDate date.</line>
				<line>The use of past sections can be minimized (using StudentWeights.PastFactor student weight).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Accommodations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Besides of students requiring short distances, additional criteria based on student accommodations were created:
					<line>Students requiring short distances (SD accommodation, there is a conflict when classes are back-to-back and distance in minutes is above zero)</line>
					<line>Students needing some time free (FT accommodation, a higher penalization for free-time conflicts)</line>
					<line>Students needing back-to-back classes (BTB accommodation, a penalization for classes that are more than 30 minutes of each other)</line>
					<line>Students needing breaks between classes (BBC accommodation, a penalization for classes that are back-to-back, or within 30 minutes of each other)</line>
				</line>
				<line>Please note that these accommodations are only enabled when the new Student Schedule Quality extension is being used (StudentSct.ScheduleQuality = true).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Curriculum Reservations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability for a curriculum reservation and overrides to have multiple majors.</line>
				<line>Added ability for the curriculum reservations and overrides to match on student minors.
					<line>When a reservation has both majors and minors, a student must have at least one matching minor OR one matching major.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added ability to further divide majors by using the optional concentrations.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Batch Student Solver Dashboard</name>
			<description>
				<line>Student Sectioning Dashboard renamed to Batch Student Solver Dashboard.</line>
				<line>Enrollments tab: when the mouse is hovering over course/class available space, show existing reservations in a tooltip popup (as they were loaded into the solver).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Online Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Wait-Listing</name>
			<description>
				<line>Status Check: Follow the status fall-backs when checking for wait-list option.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Deadlines</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to avoid classes that are past the deadline when computing an online schedule or suggestions.</line>
				<line>To be enabled by FindAssignment.CheckDeadlines solver configuration property (defaults to false).</line>
				<line>Deadlines are not checked when extended adds are allowed by the special registration and student agrees to explore conflicting schedule.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Past Sections</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to mark sections that are in the past.</line>
				<line>When enabled (FindAssignment.AvoidPastSections is true), the Scheduling Assistant will try to minimize the use of sections that are in the past.
						<line>That is before today, possibly adjusted by the number of days in FindAssignment.AvoidPastOffset.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Advisor Course Recommendations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to set a default advisor note.
					<line>Application property unitime.acrf.note, defaults to no note.</line>
					<line>To be used to pre-populate the Additional Notes field on the Advisor Course Recommendations page.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Finder</name>
			<description>
				<line>Instead of allowing advisors and administrators to see all courses (ignore course type check),
					there is now a new permission StudentSchedulingCanLookupAllCourses that the user role must have.
					<line>Automatically set for roles with StudentSchedulingAdvisor permission.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Online Student Scheduling Dashboard</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added tooltips for Area, Clasf, Major, Concentration, Minor and Accommodation columns (showing full name when available).</line>
				<line>Enrollments tab: when the mouse is hovering over course/class available space, show existing reservations in a tooltip popup.</line>
			</description>
		</item>

	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Examination Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Overlapping Periods</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to check for direct (student or instructor) conflicts between two examination periods that overlap in time.</line>
				<line>This is only enabled when solver configuration parameter Exams.CheckForPeriodOverlaps is set to true (defaults to false).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Examination Events</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability generate event's allocated time based on the examination length instead of the examination period length.
					<line>When enabled, a one hour long exam will only allocate one hour (plus the offsets) even when placed in a period of two hours.</line>
				</line>
				<line>To be enabled (for an examination problem) by unitime.examEvent.allocatesTimeBasedExamLength.REF application property, where REF is the examination problem reference.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Administration</title>
		<item>
			<name>Contact Us</name>
			<description>
				<line>Contact Us Email: Set reply-to email address to the email recipient.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Spring Integration</name>
			<description>
				<line>Spring Integration is now disabled by default (to avoid issues with data/unitime/import folder).</line>
				<line>To enable Spring Integration, set unitime.spring.context.integration=no-integration.xml in catalina.properties.
					<line>This will enable the data exchange imports in the data/unitime/import folder as well as the ability to configure receiving Event Management email responses.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
<release>
	<version>4.5.124</version>
	<release-date>Sat, 5 Dec 2020</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Advisor Course Recommendations</name>
			<description>
				<line>A page for the advisor to fill with a student while advising him/her on what courses to take the next term.</line>
				<line>It looks a lot like the Student Course Requests page, with a few fields added (credits per course, notes, etc.).</line>
				<line>When opened, the advisor can look up a student and the page gets pre-populated with the existing data.</line>
				<line>The page  automatically offers course suggestions (but it is possible to put in a free text too), fills in credits, count the credit totals, etc.</line>
				<line>When submitted, there is a PDF version generated that can be printed and signed by the student.</line>
				<line>Allows for student status change when submitted; no need for the advisor to use the dashboard to change the student status.</line>
				<line>UniTime keeps record of these advisor course requests for possible auditing/reporting (what students requested versus what they have been advised, list students that have been already advised that did not fill their course requests in, etc.).</line>
				<line>Student Course Requests page can be pre-populated with these courses, or a student can review the courses filled in by the advisor.</line>
				<line>Optionally, course recommendation may contain wait-listing toggles (based on unitime.acr.waitlist parameter).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Important Course Requests</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to put a multiple levels to critical courses: Critical &gt; Important &gt; Normal.</line>
				<line>Critical course request are assigned first, then important requests, then the rest.</line>
				<line>More levels can be defined in the future, if needed.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Alternative Majors</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to load critical courses and degree plans from an alternative major.</line>
				<line>Alternative majors are identified by a student group of a particular type a student is in.
					<line>By default group type is &quot;1st Choice&quot;, and the group abbreviation is area abbv - major code.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Custom class CriticalCoursesExplorers makes use of these (implementing both CriticalCoursesProvider and DegreePlansProvider interfaces).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Priority Students</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to identify priority students (to be assigned first) by a filter query.</line>
				<line>Improved handling of priority students by the solver.</line>
				<line>Up to 5 priority tiers can be defined (Priority, Senior, Junior, Sophomore, and Frehmen).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Reservation Restrictions</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to define on a reservation whether it is inclusive or not.</line>
				<line>There is a new mode field when editing a reservation (that is not an override) which can be:
					<line>Default: using unitime.reservations.restrictionsInclusive which defaults to true.</line>
					<line>Reservation: the currently default mode (restrictions are applied at all levels).</line>
					<line>Restriction: not-inclusive mode (restrictions are only applied on the selected level).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Grade Mode / Variable Credit Customization</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to show course credit information on a particular section (not just the first one).</line>
				<line>Gradable subpart (on which the credit is shown) can be provided using the ExternalClassNameHelperInterface interface, implementing HasGradableSubpart sub-interface.</line>
				<line>Banner Integration: Show credit information on the gradable section.</line>
				<line>Banner Integration: For variable credit courses, display assigned credit returned by XE API.</line>
				<line>Special Registration: Added ability to request credit change on a variable credit course.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Online-Only Students / Courses</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to identify some students as online-only (e.g., with a student group) and restrict them to certain courses or course configurations.</line>
				<line>The restriction can be on courses (using regular expression for course name), or on course configurations (using regular expression on instructional method reference).</line>
				<line>Added ability to hide courses that do not have an online-only option from the online-only students and vice versa (students can not look them up on the Course Requests or Scheduling Assistant page).</line>
				<line>Added ability for the solver to keep out students from courses or course configurations they cannot take.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Minimal Perturbation Problem Improvements</name>
			<description>
				<line>Improved ability to re-section not-assigned course requests while the rest is kept untouched.</line>
				<line>Existing enrollments can be fixed and left unchanged, even when they are not consistent.</line>
				<line>Single Course MPP: Added ability to re-section only students in the given course or courses, while everything else is left untouched.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Other Changes &amp; Improvements</name>
			<description>
				<line>Scheduling Dashboard: Added an ability to filter by instructional method.</line>
				<line>Custom integration with a custom student attendance planning tool, showing additional meeting information on a class that a student has enrolled.</line>
				<line>Added ability to save/validate only a subset of students loaded in the student scheduling solver.</line>
				<line>Added ability to put a small penalization on online sections.
					<line>That is sections that do not have a time, that have time and no room, or that have time but the room does not check for conflicts (like the ONLINE room).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>No Substitutions</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to reuse the wait-listing toggle as No-Subs (no substitutions) when wait-listing is disabled.
					<line>Course requests that are marked as No-Subs cannot be replaced by a substitute course.</line>
					<line>There is a new parameter of student schedule status (students may or may not be allowed to mark courses as No-Subs).</line>
				</line>
				<line>It is also possible to only allow advisor recommendations to mark courses as No-Subs (students are not allow to see/set No-Subs or Wait-List toggles).
					<line>In this case, solver parameter Load.UseAdvisorWaitLists must be set to true to check for these during the data load.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Room Sharing</name>
			<description>
				<line>More precise computation of allowed room sharing (how much space is needed in a room).</line>
				<line>This is to avoid issues when three or more classes can share a room and some of these classes do not overlap.
					<line>For example, no more than two classes overlap when there is a Monday class, a Wednesday class, and a Monday-Wednesday class.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Fixed Time MPP</name>
			<description>
				<line>A new ability to assign new rooms while the existing time assignments are left unchanged.</line>
				<line>Fixed Times: all assigned classes have only the assigned time in the domain (time preferences are completely ignored).</line>
				<line>Weakened Distributions: allow hard distribution preferences to be weakened (strongly discouraged instead of prohibited etc.)</line>
				<line>Instructor Conflicts: instructor conflicts can be allowed but penalized.</line>
				<line>Prohibited Rooms: allowed prohibited rooms in the domain (except of rooms that are too small, or not being available for the department).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Other Changes &amp; Improvements</name>
			<description>
				<line>Class Assignment: When checking for event conflicts, ignore conflicts for rooms that have the conflict checking disabled.</line>
				<line>Instructional Offering Cross Lists: Added ability to edit Reserved space (course limit) even when there is only a single course in the cross-list.</line>
				<line>Course Timetabling Save &amp; Commit: when saving &amp; committing two or more problems together, do not check for conflicts between problems that are being committed.</line>
				<line>Instructor Availability: When checking instructor availability based on events (and possibly classes from other academic sessions), also check for distance conflicts between the class and the unavailability.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Examination Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Other Changes &amp; Improvements</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added support for rooms that do not check for conflicts (e.g., the ONLINE room).</line>
				<line>Allow for examination periods to run over midnight.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Event Management</title>
		<item>
			<name>Other Changes &amp; Improvements</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to make the Expected Attendance a required field.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Other</title>
		<item>
			<name>Right-to-Left Support</name>
			<description>
				<line>Basic support for right-to-left languages.</line>
				<line>Enable by using ar locale.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>APIs</name>
			<description>
				<line>HQL Reports: Added ability to export HQL reports in JSON format using the API.</line>
				<line>Data Exchange: Course Offerings XML import and export extended to include number of rooms of a class.</line>
				<line>Data Exchange: Include export and import of advisor recommendations with the Student Course Requests XML.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Other Changes &amp; Improvements</name>
			<description>
				<line>People Lookup: Added ability to search the whole subtree in the LDAP search.</line>
				<line>Task Scheduler: make sure current month is included if it is within 12 months before session start or after session end.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
</release-history>
