<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="Release-Notes.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE release-history PUBLIC "-//UniTime//UniTime Release Notes DTD/EN" "Release-Notes.dtd">
<!--
 * Licensed to The Apereo Foundation under one or more contributor license
 * agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for
 * additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 *
 * The Apereo Foundation licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
 * Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
 * compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at:
 *
 * http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 *
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 *
 -->

<release-history>

<doc-title>UniTime 4.4 Release Notes</doc-title>
<release>
	<version>4.4.${build.number}</version>
	<release-date>${build.date}</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Batch Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Database Load: Learning Community Reservations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Corrected a minor issue with a Learning Community reservation:
					<line>
						When a course is solely reserved for a single learning community,
						and there are some students already enrolled that are not matching the provided student filter,
						the reservation limit may be updated so that it is one student less than it should be.
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>CPSolver updated to version 1.3.177 (was 1.3.176)</title>
		<item>
			<name>Student Scheduling: Enrollment</name>
			<description>
				<line>Enrollment: include reservation in the equality checking.</line>
				<line>This fixes an issue with solution restore
					(current solution containing the same enrollment, but without the reservation).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>4.4.114</version>
	<release-date>Tue, 25 Jun 2019</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Published Schedule Runs</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added an ability to publish results of solver runs for the advisors and schedule deputies to see.</line>
				<line>Published solver runs are stored in the database. It is possible to get back to a particular run.</line>
				<line>It is now possible to start a test run automatically, e.g., on a nightly basis.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Reporting</name>
			<description>
				<line>Additional solver reports have been added on the Student Sectioning Solver Reports and the Online Student Scheduling Reports pages.
					<line>Tableau report providing information for further processing (requested / enrolled courses by individual students and their properties).</line>
					<line>Critical course requests and their assignments.</line>
				</line>
				<line>There is a new API that can be used to download a solver report of the last published run.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Credit Checking</name>
			<description>
				<line>Improved handling of maximum credits of a student: a student cannot get more than max credit, it is no longer needed to move course requests that are over the max credit to alternates.</line>
				<line>Added ability to maximize the number of students that have at least a minimum number of credits.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Schedule Quality</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added an ability to optimize the following criteria:
					<line>Avoid early morning and late evening times</line>
					<line>Have time for lunch</line>
					<line>Minimize overall travel</line>
					<line>Avoid holes in the schedule (prefer back-to-back)</line>
					<line>Avoid long days (aka work-day constraint)</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Preferences and Requirements</name>
			<description>
				<line>Improved performance of the solver (added ability to swap students in order to improve Selection preference).</line>
				<line>It is now possible to put a preference on the default (not-set) instructional method.</line>
				<line>It is now possible to require certain sections or instructional methods.</line>
				<line>It is possible to define who can set required preferences (student by status, admin/advisor by permissions).</line>
				<line>It is possible to filter by preferences or requirements on the dashboard.
					<line>By individual method or section</line>
					<line>Any, all met or all unmet preferences or requirements</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Scheduling Dashboard</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added pagination when showing too many students (over 500).</line>
				<line>Enrollment counts: exclude requests that are pending, canceled, and/or rejected (depending on the override filter).</line>
				<line>Student groups have been split by type (there is a column for each type, they are grouped by type in the filter as well).</line>
				<line>Added ability to select multiple courses in the filter.</line>
				<line>Corrected computation of available space on disabled (no-print) sections.</line>
				<line>Various performance improvements.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Reservations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Course requests that have matching (individual or student group) reservations may not be removed by the student.
					<line>Such course requests may not be allowed to be changed in priority, or no alternatives can be added to them.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added more customizable individual and student group override reservations.</line>
				<line>Reservations can be edited without locking the offering when wait-listing is disabled.</line>
				<line>Created Learning Community reservations combining course and student group reservations.</line>
				<line>Various improvements on the Reservations page (e.g., it is now possible to filter by override type).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Critical Courses</name>
			<description>
				<line>Some course requests may be identified as critical.</line>
				<line>Critical course requests should take precedence (assign critical courses first, do not unassing critical course demands).</line>
				<line>Critical courses are identified by a custom class implementing the CriticalCoursesProvider interface/</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Other Improvements</name>
			<description>
				<line>Student Status: Added session-dependent student statuses.</line>
				<line>Batch Solver: do not put students into classes that already started (added General.ClassesFixedDate solver parameter).</line>
				<line>Course Requests: Alternate Course Requests renamed to Substitute Course Requests.</line>
				<line>Course Requests: Added ability to select multiple courses in the Course Finder dialog and filter by UCC course attributes.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Student Course Demands</name>
			<description>
				<line>Course Requests With Projected Last Likes: added ability to combine pre-registration (course requests) with projected last-like course enrollment data.
					<line>Course Requests take precedence, Last-Likes are weighted to fill the remaining space based on the curriculum projection rules.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Student Course Requests: Improved ability to consider course request alternatives.
					<line>Alternatives are either ignored (when StudentCourseRequests.IncludeAlternatives is false).</line>
					<line>Student weight is spread between the requested course and its alternatives, student conflicts between
						alternatives are ignored (when StudentCourseRequests.IncludeAlternatives is true, which is the default).</line>
				</line>
				<line>Curricula Requests Course Demands: improved ability to consider course request alternatives.
					<line>Alternatives are either ignored (when StudentCourseRequests.IncludeAlternatives is false).
						Course requests are included in the curriculum problem.</line>
					<line>Student weight is spread between the requested course and its alternatives, student conflicts between alternatives are
						ignored (when StudentCourseRequests.IncludeAlternatives is true, which is the default).
						While course requests (without alternatives) are included in the curriculum, true requests with alternatives
						are used in the timetabling for students that are not made up.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Event Management</title>
		<item>
			<name>Permissions</name>
			<description>
				<line>Finer control over who can see unpublished class events.
					<line>When unitime.events.hasRole.checkSessionStatusForClasses is set to true (departmental managers cannot see unpublished class events of other departments).</line>
					<line>Allow some department-dependent roles to see all class events with the new EventCanSeeUnpublishedEvents permission.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Approval</name>
			<description>
				<line>When new meetings of a Special or Course-Related event are automatically approved (either due to the Approve New Meetings toggle or the event status), also add Approve action into the event notes.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Administration</title>
		<item>
			<name>Data Exchange</name>
			<description>
				<line>CSV Exports: Added ability to export CSVs with custom delimiter and quotation characters.
					<line>Using csvDelimiter and csvQuatation parameters, for example: &amp;csvDelimiter=%7c&amp;csvQuotation= will add | as delimiter and no quotation marks.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Course Offering Export: export class.managingDept when a class is externally managed.</line>
				<line>Academic Session Import: Corrected import of automated tasks (do not create a script if it already exists, do not limit script length to 255 chars).</line>
				<line>Solver Load: Added ability to load solver XML in using the Data Exchange page.
					<line>No data are updated, but the appropriate solver is created and loaded in using the given XML file.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Dependencies</name>
			<description>
				<line>Spring Framework upgraded to 4.3.18 (was 3.2.14)</line>
				<line>spring Security upgraded to 4.2.9 (was 3.2.8)</line>
				<line>Spring Integration upgraded to 4.3.17 (was 3.0.7)</line>
				<line>Appache Commons FileUpload updated to version 1.3.3 (was 1.3.1)</line>
				<line>Restlet Framework upgraded to 2.3.12 (was 2.3.4)</line>
				<line>Added jaxen 1.1.6 to ensure that scripts are able to create XML files (this fixes an issue ClassNotFoundException: org.jaxen.VariableContext).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>OpenStreetMap</name>
			<description>
				<line>Use OpenStreetMap as default on rooms and buildings.</line>
				<line>Cache map tiles within UniTime.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Other</name>
			<description>
				<line>Sponsoring Organizations: Avoid a Hibernate cache exception when deleting a sponsoring organization that is being used.</line>
				<line>Date Patterns: Avoid throwing an error when the date pattern starts before the first month (just ignore the dates before instead).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
</release-history>
