<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="Release-Notes.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE release-history PUBLIC "-//UniTime//UniTime Release Notes DTD/EN" "Release-Notes.dtd">
<!--
 * Licensed to The Apereo Foundation under one or more contributor license
 * agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for
 * additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 *
 * The Apereo Foundation licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
 * Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
 * compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at:
 *
 * http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 *
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 *
 -->

<release-history>

<doc-title>UniTime 4.7 Release Notes</doc-title>

<release>
	<version>4.7.${build.number}</version>
	<release-date>${build.date}</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Timetable Grid: Hide Auxiliary Instructors</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added an ability to hide instructors with auxiliary responsibilities.
					<line>When class instructors are used (instead of solution instructors), hide instructors with auxiliary teaching responsibilities.</line>
					<line>A teaching responsibility can be marked as Auxiliary on the Administration &gt; Other &gt; Teaching Responsibilities page.</line>
					<line>The conflicts are still checked for such instructors and they show when the data are loaded into the solver.
						<line>They only do not show when there is no solver loaded in memory for the user,</line>
						<line>or for committed solutions of other problems (when unitime.timeGrid.fixInstructors is also set to true).</line>
					</line>
				</line>
				<line>Enabled when tmtbl.timeGrid.useClassInstructors.hideAuxiliary is set to true (defaults to false).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Timetable Grid: Class Filter</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to filter by instructional offering configuration name, for example config:1</line>
				<line>The value is a regular expression that the configuration name must match.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Distribution Type: Same Days-Time-Weeks</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added Same Days-Time-Weeks distribution type (SAME_DTW).
					<line>Given classes must be taught at the same time of day, on the same days and on the same weeks (i.e., must have the same date pattern).
						<line>It is the combination of Same Days, Same Time, and Same Weeks distribution preferences.</line>
					</line>
					<line>When prohibited or (strongly) discouraged: Any pair of classes classes cannot be taught on the same days during the same time and during overlapping date patterns.
						<line>In other words, the given classes cannot overlap.</line>
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Administration</title>
		<item>
			<name>Data Exchange: Scripts, Reports</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added an ability to export all scripts and all HQL reports using the Data Exchange page.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Bug Fixes</title>
		<item>
			<name>Add/Edit Solver Configuration: Date Parameters</name>
			<description>
				<line>Use yyyy-MM-dd format for parameters of date type.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Add/Edit Solver Configuration: Validation</name>
			<description>
				<line>When the validation of the Add/Edit Solver Configuration page fails, ensure that
					<line>default parameters are loaded in,</line>
					<line>add/edit operation is preserved, and</line>
					<line>field errors are displayed.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Timetabling Solver Load: Distributions</name>
			<description>
				<line>When a distribution with One of Each or Pairwise structure is used
					<line>estimate the number of individual distribution constraints that would be posted,</line>
					<line>if there are over 1,000 of them &gt; print a warning</line>
					<line>if there are over 10,000 of them &gt; print an error, ignore the distribution preference.</line>
				</line>
				<line>This is to prevent speed / out-of-memory issues, especially when one-of-each is used as it can lead to a lot of individual constraints.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
<release>
	<version>4.7.91</version>
	<release-date>Thu, 6 Apr 2023</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Online Conflicts</name>
			<description>
				<line>Online/Offline Room: Added a distribution constraints Online/Offline Room that prevents (or penalizes) a pair of classes
				which are taught on the same day and one is placed in and online room and the other is not.</line>
				<line>No Student Online Conflicts: Added a global constraint No Student Online Conflicts that prevents a student from having
					two classes on the same day, one being online and the other not.
					<line>To be registered by setting General.GlobalConstraints=org.cpsolver.coursett.constraint.NoStudentOnlineConflicts.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Online classes are identified by a regular expression matching the room name and set in the General.OnlineRoom parameter.
					<line>It defaults to (?i)ONLINE|</line>
					<line>Classes without a room are considered online when the parameter matches a blank string.</line>
					<line>If a class has multiple rooms, all rooms must be online for the class to be considered online.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Batch Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Learning Communities: Reservations Priority</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added a new LC priority level (as the very first one).</line>
				<line>To be used for courses with LC reservations (by setting solver parameter Load.LCRequestPriority=LC).</line>
				<line>This is to ensure that LC courses are assigned first.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Online Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Email Notifications</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to provide source-action for user/externally initiated emails.</line>
				<line>When showing advisor recommendations, include Critical column when there is at least one course marked as critical.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Bug Fixes</title>
		<item>
			<name>Examination Timetable: Instructor Timetable</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed a NullPointerException thrown when there is an instructor that is assigned only to an exam (or exams) that is not loaded in the solver.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructor Detail: Teaching Preference</name>
			<description>
				<line>Corrected the teaching preference permission check on the Instructor Detail page.</line>
				<line>This fixes the NumberFormatException when the instructor's teaching preference is Prohibited but the maximal teaching load is set.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Solver Parameters: Visible</name>
			<description>
				<line>Make sure that a new parameter is created as visible when the Visible toggle is not changed (which returns null).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Class Detail: Parent Class</name>
			<description>
				<line>Corrected Parent Class link.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Academic Session Import: Curriculum Reservations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fix CurriculumReservation.area -&gt; CurriculumReservation.areas when importing session from an older instance of UniTime (before the change of the relation to academic areas from one-to-many to many-to-many).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
<release>	
	<version>4.7.81</version>
	<release-date>Sat, 4 Mar 2023</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Re-Scheduling</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added a re-scheduling mode to the wait-listing: It does not allow for wait-listing, but students can be moved around when there was a change and re-scheduling is enabled.</line>
				<line>On an instructional offering (Edit Course Offering for the controlling course), the Wait-Listing can be either
					<line>Wait-Listing Enabled,</line>
					<line>Re-Scheduling Enabled -- this is the new mode,</line>
					<line>Wait-Listing Disabled.</line>
				</line>
				<line>The default setting (property unitime.offering.waitListDefault) can now be WaitList, ReSchedule, or Disabled, with the default being Disabled.</line>
				<line>There is now a new student status scheduling toggle (Re-Scheduling) that indicates whether the student status allows for re-scheduling.</line>
				<line>When automatically moving students around, added ability to avoid sections that have already started.
					<line>This can be enabled by setting unitime.sectioning.config.ReScheduling.AvoidPastSections to true.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added ability to ignore time conflicts where two classes are overlapping only over the break time of the first one.
					<line>To enable set unitime.sectioning.config.ReScheduling.IgnoreBreakTimeConflicts to true (defaults to false, break time conflicts are not allowed).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Finder</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to filter out courses that do not have any classes that are enabled for student scheduling.</line>
				<line>To enable, set unitime.custom.CourseMatcherProvider=org.unitime.timetable.onlinesectioning.match.SkipDisabledCourseMatcher</line>
				<line>When OnlineOnlyCourseMatcherProvider is used already, set unitime.sectioning.config.Filter.ShowDisabled=false instead.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Student Online Conflicts</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added an experimental criterion that tries to minimize cases where a student has an online and in-person class on the same day.</line>
				<line>Online classes are identified by a regular expression matching the room name and set in the StudentConflict.OnlineRoom parameter
					<line>it defaults to (?i)(ONLINE|) -- room name is ONLINE or there is no room assigned</line>
					<line>classes without a room are considered online when the parameter matches a blank string</line>
					<line>if a class has multiple rooms, all rooms must be online for the class to be considered online</line>
				</line>
				<line>The criterion is weighted by the Comparator.StudentOnlineConflictWeight parameter, defaults to one half of the Comparator.StudentConflictWeight</line>
				<line>To enable add org.cpsolver.coursett.criteria.additional.StudentOnlineConflict into General.AdditionalCriteria paramete.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Assign Instructors: Copy Instructor Assignments to Sub-Subparts</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to copy instructor assignments to children classes of the same instructional type, e.g., from Lec 1 to Lec 1a and Lec 1b.</line>
				<line>Only enabled when unitime.instructors.copyToSubSubparts is set to true (defaults to false).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>	
	<category>
		<title>Administration</title>
		<item>
			<name>Clustering: custom timeouts and other parameters</name>
			<description>
				<line>For the TCP configurations of the hibernate, sectioning, and the solver cluster,
					the following parameters have been added so that they can be configured without modifying the XML configuration file:
					<line># TCP &amp; TCPPING protocols -- port range</line>
					<line>jgroups.tcp.port_range=3</line>
					<line># FD protocol -- time limit and the number of tries</line>
					<line>jgroups.fd.timeout=5000</line>
					<line>jgroups.fd.max_tries=5</line>
					<line># FD_SOCK protocol - ports, 0 means to pick a random port above 10000</line>
					<line>jgroups.fd_sock.port_range=50</line>
					<line>jgroups.fd_sock.start_port=0</line>
					<line>jgroups.fd_sock.client_bind_port=0</line>
					<line># VERIFY_SUSPECT protocol -- time limit</line>
					<line>jgroups.verify_suspect.timeout=2500</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>LDAP Lookup: Additional Properties</name>
			<description>
				<line>The following application properties have been added in order to make the LDAP people lookup more configurable.
					<line>LDAP context referral (no referral is set when left not set): tmtbl.lookup.ldap.referral</line>
					<line>LDAP attributes:
						<line>user id: tmtbl.lookup.ldap.uid</line>
						<line>full name: tmtbl.lookup.ldap.cn</line>
						<line>last name: tmtbl.lookup.ldap.sn</line>
						<line>first name: tmtbl.lookup.ldap.givenName</line>
					</line>
					<line>Added ability to skip entries without email: when tmtbl.lookup.ldap.skipWhenNoEmail is set to true (defaults to false).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Java 20 Support</name>
			<description>
				<line>ASM updated to 9.4 (was 9.2). This is to support Java 19 and Java 20.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
<release>
	<version>4.7.71</version>
	<release-date>Sat, 28 Jan 2023</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Wait-Listing</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					UniTime 4.7 includes various improvements in wait-listing,
					including the ability to swap a course or wait-list for a different section of a course that the student is already enrolled in.
				</line>
				<line>
					Also, there is a new Wait-List Preferences dialog that provides additional options to the student, including setting up a swap or
					providing section requirements.
				</line>
				<line>
					The course re-scheduling (automatic updates to student schedules after the course change) has been updated and
					made more robust. It also currently only triggers on courses that allow for wait-listing while the wait-listing is enabled.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Scheduling Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					UniTime 4.7 includes various improvements in student scheduling,
					including the ability for a student to indicate whether he/she prefers dense vs sparse schedule or online vs face-to-face classes.
				</line>
				<line>
					When enabled, a student may also require only online classes, or limit the days during which he/she can attend classes.
					<line>
						This is to better support Summer (or similar) sessions that contain multiple optional modules,
						and where students may be allowed to take some courses while not being present at the campus. 
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Override Requests: Course-specific Notes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Requests Override dialog updated to allow for course-specific notes.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Course Request Priorities</name>
			<description>
				<line>A new course request priority named Vital has been added.
					<line>The scale is now Critical &gt; Vital &gt; Important &gt; No Priority</line>
				</line>
				<line>Advisors can now set the course request priority separately from no-subs/wait-list toggle.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Funding Department</name>
			<description>
				<line>An optional funding department has been added to classes. It can be used to group the class data differently for funding reporting than it is done for course timetabling.</line>
				<line>The visibility of the funding department functionality is controlled by a property (unitime.courses.funding_departments_enabled) so it is not visible for institutions that do not use it.</line>
				<line>Finding department can be defined on multiple levels: on the subject area (for courses controlled by a course of this subject), on a course, or on an individual class.</line>
				<line>Similar to external managers, the funding department defaults to the controlling department of the class, and only departments marked as possible funding departments can be selected as additional options.</line>
				<line>A number of pages have been rewritten to GWT as part of this effort, but it is possible to switch the user interface back to the original Struts based page. See unitime.legacy.xxx properties in the Application Configuration.
					<line>These include Departments, Subject Areas, Instructor Assignment, and Add/Edit Course Offering pages.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Room Partitions</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to partition a room into multiple smaller rooms.
					<line>On the Add/Edit Room page, there is a new Partition of drop-down listing all rooms of the same building that are not partitions of some other rooms already.</line>
					<line>Non-university locations cannot be partitioned.</line>
					<line>On the Rooms page, there is a new Partitions of column (listing the parent room of room partition).</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added support for the course timetabling solver.
					<line>Parent room is unavailable when one of its partitions is occupied and vice versa (partitions cannot be used at the time when the parent class is occupied).</line>
					<line>Timetable Grid page can include:
						<line>classes from all the partitions on the parent room,</line>
						<line>classes of the parent room on each of the room partitions.</line>
						<line>This is disabled by default, enable by setting unitime.timeGrid.classesAcrossPartitions to true.</line>
					</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added support for conflict checking in the events, and for the computation and display of conflicting events.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Timetable Grid: Class Filter</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added ability to filter classes that will be listed on the Timetable page.</line>
				<line>Enable by setting unitime.timeGrid.classFilter to true in the Application Configuration.</line>
				<line>The filter may contain a boolean expression (for example: ALG or BIOL or C S).</line>
				<line>The following tags are supported:
					<line>without any tags, both class name and instructor name are matched</line>
					<line>class: match class name only</line>
					<line>instructor: match instructor name or external id only</line>
					<line>room: match assigned room</line>
					<line>limit: match class limit (e.g., limit:>100 for classes over 100)</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Daybreak Distribution Constraint</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added Daybreak constraint that checks for cases when there is an evening class and a morning class the following day.</line>
				<line>There should be at least the given number of hours between an evening class followed by a morning class the next day.</line>
				<line>The constraint can be also parameterized by a distance between the two classes:
					<line>The constraint only triggers when the distance between the two classes is over the provided distance.</line>
					<line>Distance checking is disabled when distance is set to -1.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Other</title>
		<item>
			<name>Localization: Zanata &gt; POEditor.com</name>
			<description>
				<line>Since Zanata is no longer being maintained, UniTime 4.7 translations have been moved to poeditor.com.
					<line>See https://poeditor.com/join/project/Aa5qIUPsnp for joining the translations effort.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Single PO file per locale is now being used for data exchange.</line>
				<line>Updated ant tasks for import/export scripts, added ability to automatically download PO file and update UniTime.gwt.xml config.</line>
				<line>To build UniTime for a different language, for example German, just use
					<line>ant -Dlocale=de import-translations build</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Dependencies: Apache Struts 2</name>
			<description>
				<line>All the Struts-based pages have been migrated to Apache Struts 2 (from Apache Struts 1).
					<line>There are only minor cosmetic changes, but all the URLs that used to have .do are now .action.</line>
				</line>
				<line>With this change, all pages can now be localized.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
</release-history>
