<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="Release-Notes.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE release-history PUBLIC "-//UniTime//UniTime Release Notes DTD/EN" "Release-Notes.dtd">
<!--
 * Licensed to The Apereo Foundation under one or more contributor license
 * agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for
 * additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 *
 * The Apereo Foundation licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
 * Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
 * compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at:
 *
 * http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 *
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 *
 -->

<release-history>

<doc-title>UniTime 4.7 Release Notes</doc-title>
<release>
	<version>4.7.${build.number}</version>
	<release-date>${build.date}</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>Student Scheduling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Wait-Listing</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					UniTime 4.7 will include various improvements in wait-listing,
					including the ability to swap a course or wait-list for a different section of a course that the student is already enrolled in.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Scheduling Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					UniTime 4.7 will include various improvements in student scheduling,
					including the ability for a student to indicate whether he/she prefers dense vs sparse schedule or online vs face-to-face classes.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Course Timetabling</title>
		<item>
			<name>Funding Department</name>
			<description>
				<line>An optional funding department has been added to classes. It can be used to group the class data differently for funding reporting than it is done for course timetabling.</line>
				<line>The visibility of the funding department functionality is controlled by a property (unitime.courses.funding_departments_enabled) so it is not visible for institutions that do not use it.</line>
				<line>Finding department can be defined on multiple levels: on the subject area (for courses controlled by a course of this subject), on a course, or on an individual class.</line>
				<line>Similar to external managers, the funding department defaults to the controlling department of the class, and only departments marked as possible funding departments can be selected as additional options.</line>
				<line>A number of pages have been rewritten to GWT as part of this effort, but it is possible to switch the user interface back to the original Struts based page. See unitime.legacy.xxx properties in the Application Configuration.
					<line>These include Departments, Subject Areas, Instructor Assignment, and Add/Edit Course Offering pages.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>
</release-history>
