<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="Release-Notes.css"?>
<!-- 
 * UniTime 3.0 (University Course Timetabling & Student Sectioning Application)
 * Copyright (C) 2007, UniTime.org
 * 
 * This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
 * it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
 * the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
 * (at your option) any later version.
 * 
 * This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
 * but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 * MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
 * GNU General Public License for more details.
 * 
 * You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 * with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 * 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA.
 -->

<release-history>

<doc-title>Timetabling - Release Notes</doc-title>

<release>
	<version>3.0.@build.number@</version>
	<release-date>@release.date@</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Rooms</name>
			<description>
				<line>For external manager with only one department (e.g., LAB) -- display the rooms of the department right away.</line>
				<line>Fixed display problem of departmental room features (sometimes, multiple features were displayed in a single row).</line>
				<line>Table ordering corrected (each table can be ordered separately, but only ordering of the class rooms table was actually used).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Rooms, Room Features, Room Groups</name>
			<description>
				<line>For external manager with only one department (e.g., LAB) -- display Export PDF button next to other buttons (Search/Export PDF component is not present).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Data Import</name>
			<description>
				<line>StudentImport and LastLikeCourseDemandImport are now inherited from BaseImport.</line>
				<line>StudentImport: speed improved by not using StudentDAO.save(student); all students for given academic session are deleted first</line>
				<line>LastLikeCourseDemandImport: all last-like course demands for given academic session are deleted first</line>
				<line>Data Import page now uploads the selected file (using Struts file upload).</line>
				
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Cloning</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added methods for cloning of instructional offerings and all underlaying objects (configurations, subparts, classes, etc).</line>
			</description>
		</item>		
	</category>
	
	<version>3.0.22</version>
	<release-date>Wed, 27 Jun 2007</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Rooms</name>
			<description>
				<line>Room Features, Room Groups: Abbreviation column added</line>
				<line>Room Detail, Room Edit: Administrator can see and change external id.</line>
				<line>Room Detail, Room Edit: Administrator can change room type (property Room.scheduledRoomType).</line>
				<line>Allow Add Special Use Room only when external rooms are populated for the given session.</line>
				<line>Added add any room capability (administrator only).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offering Cross Lits</name>
			<description>
				<line>Made screen more intuitive.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Date Patterns</name>
			<description>
				<line>Display of the selected date pattern corrected.</line>
				<line>Fix Generated feature improved
					<line>replace the generated date pattern with an existing one if the difference is not more than 5 days</line>
					<line>otherwise rename the generated date pattern to "generated start - end" where start and end are start and end days in MM/dd format</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Administration</name>
			<description>
				<line>Subject Areas: Struts configuration corrected.</line>
				<line>Buildings: Add/update/delete functions added.</line>
				<line>Buildings, Timetable Managers, Departments, Subject Areas, Solver Groups: Export PDF function added.</line>
				<line>Application Config: Display all effective properties set for the application.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Menu</name>
			<description>
				<line>FAQ and Tips &amp; Tricks pages moved to wiki.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructors</name>
			<description>
				<line>Instructor Lookup: Fixed problem with I2A2 lookup (No getter method for property: "puid" of bean: "i2a2") -- User object has no longer method getPuid(), but it has getId().</line>
				<line>Instructor Delete: Fixed hibernate problem (deleted object would be re-saved by cascade) when an instructor with some class assignments was deleted.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Distribution Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>Distribution preferences that are set on instructors were not filtered by course number, this is now corrected.</line>
				<line>Add/Edit Distribution Preference: Compare classes using ClassComparator, not by their unique ids.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Student Sectioning</name>
			<description>
				<line>Load academic areas, classifications, majors, and minors</line>
				<line>Solver update, https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/cpsolver-cvs for more details.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Database</name>
			<description>
				<line>Database connection properties can be set in custom.property file</line>
				<line>Buildings: Minor change to remove non-existent building as part of update process.</line>
				<line>Major Import: Create empty set for academic areas if null.</line>
				<line>Configuration Edit: Fixed org.hibernate.PropertyAccessException (Exception occurred inside setter of org.unitime.timetable.model.Class_.managingDept)</line>
				<line>ChangeLog: queries made cacheable.</line>
				<line>Last-like Course Demands Import: speed up -- cache the SubjectAreas and CourseOfferings.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Other</name>
			<description>
				<line>Timetabling CSS: Fixed a bug.</line>
				<line>WebTable: Removed italic tag and instead depend on css to do all formatting</line>
				<line>Changed logos to remove SMAS and put unitime.org.</line>
				<line>File footer.jsp removed -- it is not used.</line>
				<line>Tags propertyEquals and propertyNotEquals added.</line>
				<line>Use property tags instead of using ApplicationProperties class directly in JSPs.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>

	<version>3.0.19</version>
	<release-date>Wed, 13 Jun 2007</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>ALL MODULES</title>
		<item>
			<name>First Open Source Release</name>
			<description>
				<line>This is a first Open Source release of this application.</line>
				<line>See http://www.unitime.org for more details.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

</release-history>