<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="Release-Notes.css"?>
<!-- 
 * UniTime 3.0 (University Course Timetabling & Student Sectioning Application)
 * Copyright (C) 2007, UniTime.org
 * 
 * This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
 * it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
 * the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
 * (at your option) any later version.
 * 
 * This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
 * but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 * MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
 * GNU General Public License for more details.
 * 
 * You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 * with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 * 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA.
 -->

<release-history>

<doc-title>Timetabling - Release Notes</doc-title>

<release>
	<version>3.0.@build.number@</version>
	<release-date>@release.date@</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offering Config, Multiple Class Setup</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Default room group might not be set; in such a case, create no default room group 
					preference rather than throwing an exception.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Edit Academic Session</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed some database/hibernate issues with a deletion of an academic session.</line>
				<line>Added check so that a user cannot delete the very last one academic session.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Departments</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Added toggle: Show all departments (including departments with no manager and no subject area) 
					that allows a user to see all departments (by default, only departments that are being used 
					for timetabling are displayed).
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Edit Department</name>
			<description>
				<line>Column Externally Managed renamed to External Manager.</line>
				<line>External Manager flag cannot be changed if:
					<line>There is one or more subject areas associated with the department.</line>
					<line>The department is marked as external manager, and there are classes that are managed by the department.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added delete department functionality.
					<line>A department cannot be deleted if there is a solver group associated with it,</line>
					<line>or if there is course that is offered in one of its subject areas.</line>
					<line>
						If an externally managed department is about to be deleted, all classes that 
						are managed by the department are changed to be departmental (old room and 
						distribution preferences are deleted)
					</line>
				</line>
				<line>Delete department: display confirmation
					<line>The department and all associated data will be deleted. Continue?</line>
				</line>
				<line>On delete: added change log message, clear hibernate cache to prevent cache problems (e.g., while displaying timetabling managers).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Timetables</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed MySQL problem in solution delete.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Select User Role</name>
			<description>
				<line>Selection of user role and academic session redesigned in order to tackle the following problems:
					<line>Academic initiative was not considered at all (can become a problem if the application is to be used for more than one campus).</line>
					<line>Ordering of listed sessions was inconsistent (e.g., it was different for Administrator role and other roles).</line>
					<line>Ability to display additional session information (e.g., academic initiative, session status).</line>
					<line>Ability to display current selection (if used to change current user role / academic session).</line>
					<line>Department code does not need to be of length 4.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Users with "View All" role:
					<line>If the user has associated one or more departments, he/she can access only academic sessions of these departments.</line>
					<line>If the user has no department associated, he/she can see all the academic sessions.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Edit Subject Area</name>
			<description>
				<line>A subject area can only be associated with a department that is not marked as external manager.</line>
				<line>When a department of a subject area is changed:
					<line>Managing department of all DEPARTMENTAL classes of the subject area is also changed to the new department.
						<line>This also deletes existing class assignments of the affected classes.</line>
					</line>
					<line>Instructor assignments of all classes of the subject area are changed as follows:
						<line>An instructor from the new department is used if there is one with the same external id in the new department,</line>
						<line>instructor assignment is deleted otherwise.</line>
					</line>
					<line>Room, building, room group and room feature preferences of all DEPARTMENTAL classes of the subject area are deleted if
						<line>Room / building is not shared with the new department</line>
						<line>Room group / feature is departmental (not global)</line>
					</line>
					<line>Ownership of all distribution preferences that are owned by the old department and that have first class/subpart from the subject area are changed to the new department.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Hide delete button when a subject area cannot be deleted.</line>
				<line>Disable department selection when a department cannot be changed (i.e., when there is a committed solution).</line>
				<line>On delete: added change log message, clear hibernate cache to prevent cache problems (e.g., while displaying departments).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Types</name>
			<description>
				<line>Table of instructional types made sortable, some columns were renamed.</line>
				<line>Added export PDF.</line>
				<line>Added add/modify/delete itype capabilities.
					<line>An itype can only be deleted, if it is not used (there is no scheduling subpart with the given itype).</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Timetable Managers</name>
			<description>
				<line>Column "External Id" renamed to "External ID".</line>
				<line>Do not display role icons.</line>
				<line>Do not display external manager role (there is no such role), display externally managed departments in bold instead.</line>
				<line>Last Change column: display message of pattern "page (operation) on date" instead of "date by user"
					<line>
						This way, it is more clear that the column displays the most recent change made by the manager 
						(not when and by whom the manager was changed for the last time).
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Edit Timetable Manager</name>
			<description>
				<line>Check for existence of another manager with the same External IDs on update as well.</line>
				<line>Do not display role icons.</line>
				<line>Do not display external manager role (there is no such role).</line>
				<line>Display role abbreviations instead of references.</line>
				<line>If there is only one role selected, it is automatically marked as primary.</line>
				<line>
					Only users with Department Schedule Manager role have to have at least one 
					department associated (administrator and view only users do not need to have a department).
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Users</name>
			<description>
				<line>Column "External Id" renamed to "External ID".</line>
				<line>Fixed problem with changing user name (identifier of an instance of User was altered).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Date Patterns</name>
			<description>
				<line>Date Patterns screen made more intuitive and consistent with other screens.
					<line>Either list of date patterns or the add/edit date pattern form are displayed.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Column Default removed (default date pattern is printed in bold instead).</line>
				<line>Column Visible removed (not visible date patterns are printed in gray instead).</line>
				<line>On save / update / back, the page is scrolled down to the last edited date pattern.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Time Patterns</name>
			<description>
				<line>Time Patterns screen made more intuitive and consistent with other screens.
					<line>Either list of time patterns or the add/edit time pattern form are displayed.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Column Visible removed (not visible time patterns are printed in gray instead).</line>
				<line>On save / update / back, the page is scrolled down to the last edited time pattern.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Database Load</name>
			<description>
				<line>Loading of last-like course demand:
					<line>Use course offering permanent id, if it is set and match with some last-like course demands,</line>
					<line>use subject area / course number otherwise.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Suggestions</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Fixed problem with some classes being "mysteriously" unassigned when Suggestion screen 
					was used on a solution loaded using automated (not-interactive) solver due to:
					<line>Section Placements of Suggestions screen is used.</line>
					<line>A wrong class get unassigned during assignment of a suggestion</line>
				</line>
				<line>
					The problem was caused by constraints that returns a set of conflicting constraints 
					in a non-deterministic way (e.g., spread in time constraint with initial allowance 
					over 2 classes per a time slot -- e.g., spread of 21 or more classes over 10 
					possible times). Undo of a tested placement or assignment of a suggestion was done 
					in a way that did not anticipated a possibility of a different set of conflicting 
					classes to be returned (different than during assignment of the tested placement / suggestion). 
					To overcome this problem, all assignments that are to be changed need to be 
					unassigned first, and then assigned to the new values.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Solver Configurations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Solver Settings screen changed to Solver Configurations.</line>
				<line>Configuration export operation corrected.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Solver Definitions</name>
			<description>
				<line>Solver Definition page removed from menu
					<line>Since every solution info needs to be implemented anyway, it is not desired to change implementation class in the user interface.</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Constraint Solver</name>
			<description>
				<line>Constraint solver updated, see https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/cpsolver-cvs for more details.</line> 
				<line>Major changes:
					<line>On fly student sectioning -- fixed problem with committed student conflict counter.</line>
					<line>Message level of "Nothing to solve." changed to ERROR (was FATAL).</line>
				</line>
			</description> 
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Database</name>
			<description>
				<line>MySQL: added script blank-data.sql
					<line>
						This scripts truncates all the timetabling tables and populates read-only tables 
						with initial values. It also creates an administrator user (admin/admin) and 
						an academic session with one department and a solver group.
					</line>
				</line>
				<line>Course permanent ids:
					<line>Added index on course permanent id column of LASTLIKE_COURSE_DEMAND table.</line>
					<line>Allow course permanent id of a course offering to be NULL.</line>
					<line>Set course permanent id to NULL whenever set to -1 for all last-like course requests.</line>
					<line>Set course permanent id to NULL whenever set to -1 for all course offerings.</line>
				</line>
				<line>Added MySQL versions of existing change scripts.</line>
				<line>Property ItypeDesc.smas_abbv removed, property ItypeDesc.abbv is used instead.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>3.0.26</version>
	<release-date>Fri, 28 Sep 2007</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offerings</name>
			<description>
				<line>PDF Export: Horizontal alignment of the time preference column changed to left (was center).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offering Detail</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fix bug in IE: external link should open in a new window.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Edit Course Offering</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Fixed problem "The course cannot be renamed. A course with the same course number already exists." when a course offering edit 
					screen was used on a non-controlling cross-listed course of a different subject area than the controlling course but with the 
					same course number as the controlling course.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offering Cross Lists</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Fixed bug: When the change in cross-list results in a change of controlling department of an instructional offering, 
					all departmental classes (i.e., classes that are managed by the controlling department) have to have their managing 
					department changed to the new controlling department.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Solver</title>
		<item>
			<name>Database Load</name>
			<description>
				<line>
					Property General.DepartmentIds was not correctly computed in the case when multiple solver groups were loaded together 
					-- it did contain only departments of the first solver group.
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Other</name>
			<description>
				<line>Constraint solver updated, see https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/cpsolver-cvs for more details.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Data Import</name>
			<description>
				<line>Import of Academic Area Reservations: Skip over a reservation if the academic area is not found.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Database</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed problems with creation of the database schema for certain versions of MySQL (table APPLICATION_CONFIG).
					<line>Fixed problem ERROR 1071 (specified key was too long) on table application_config.</line>
					<line>Fixed problem ERROR 1170 (BLOB/TEXT column 'name' used in key specification without a key length) that occurred on MySQL 4.1.</line> 
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>3.0.25</version>
	<release-date>Tue, 4 Sep 2007</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Edit Course Offering</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fix parse exception caused by non numeric io limit.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Reservations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Print instructional offering limit.</line>
				<line>Course Reservations (on a class):
					<line>Fixed problem: The instructional offering limit is not displayed.</line>
					<line>Fixed problem: If there are two courses listed in a reservation on a class and the user wants to delete the first one (clicks on the Delete button next to the first one), the second course is deleted instead.</line></line>
				<line>Fix parse exception cause by non numeric io limit.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offering Cross Lists</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed hibernate exception.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Multiple Class Setup</name>
			<description>
				<line>Updated display of schedule subpart limits</line>
				<line>Added ability to mark all classes of a subpart as display instructors.</line>
				<line>Added ability to mark all classes of a subpart as display in schedule.</line>
				<line>Fixed bug with Display All Instructors and Display All in Schedule.</line>
				<line>Changed <i>Display Instructors</i> and <i>Display in Schedule</i> to show the checkmark icon (tick.gif) when they are true and the schedule deputy does not have permission to edit the field.  Used to display the word <i>true</i> or <i>false</i>.  This applies to both the subpart rows and then class rows.</line>
				<line>Added change in row background color when mousing over a subpart row.  Class rows did this already.</line>
				<line>Cleaned up alignment of scheduling subpart limit labels.</line>
				<line>Fixed Javascript Errors with subtotals in IE.</line>
				<line>Fixed Javascript Error that prevented min/max limit from being syncronized.</line>
				<line>Fixed Button alignment on bottom of screen.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offering Configuration Edit</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fix bug that deleted instr offering when a configuration was deleted.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Not-assigned Classes</name>
			<description>
				<line>Column Name renamed to Class.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Timetable Grid</name>
			<description>
				<line>Use NaturalOrderComparator for ordering cells in a timetable grid (the case when two or more classes overlap in time).</line>
				<line>Week -1 can represent the last week of the previous year (visible, e.g., for Spring 2008 term), value of selection 'All weeks' changed to -100 (was -1).</line>
				<line>Visualisation of the weeks of the previous year corrected (former reasoning "week &lt; 0 implies all weeks" was wrong in this case).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Application Configuration</name>
			<description>
				<line>Only display application properties that starts with <u>tmtbl.</u>
					<line>This feature is customizable by property <u>tmtbl.appConfig.pattern</u>, default is the regular expression <u>^tmtbl\..*$</u></line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>Solver</title>
		<item>
			<name>Solver Warnings</name>
			<description>
				<line>With every class, estimate the number of possible placements and
					<line>refuse to load a class if the number of placements exceed 1 000 000, the following error is printed:
						<line>
							Class C has too many possible placements (X).
							The class was not loaded in order to prevent out of memory exception.
							Please restrict the number of available rooms and/or times for this class.
						</line>
						<line>
							( where C is the name of the class, and X is the estimated number of placements )
						</line>
					</line>
					<line>otherwise, print the following warning if the number of placements exceed 10 000:
						<line>
							Class C has quite a lot of possible placements (X).
							Solver may run too slow.
							If possible, please restrict the number of available rooms and/or times for this class.
						</line>
						<line>
							( where C is the name of the class, and X is the estimated number of placements )
						</line>
					</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Remote Solver</name>
			<description>
				<line>Ask web server for its application properties before constructing a database connection.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Other</name>
			<description>
				<line>Constraint solver updated, see https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/cpsolver-cvs for more details.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
	<category>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Hibernate Configuration</name>
			<description>
				<line>Propagate application property default_schema into the hibernate configuration, if it is set.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Database</name>
			<description>
				<line>Size of column APPLICATION_CONFIG.NAME changed to match the hibernate configuration.</line>
				<line>Woebegon College Example: In table APPLICATION_CONFIG, property systemAccessLevel changed to tmtbl.access_level, systemMessage changed to tmtbl.system_message.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>3.0.24</version>
	<release-date>Mon, 23 Jul 2007</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Cross-lists</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed exception that occurs when course has no configurations and hence no instructional offering limit.</line>
				<line>Fix display of error message regarding mismatch in limits if the screen loads without any pre-existing reservations.</line>
				<line>Suppress display of mimatch limits if there are any blank values in the reserved spaces field.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Reservations</name>
			<description>
				<line>For reservations on class: check that the number of reservation does not exceed the number of courses in the offering.</line>
				<line>Allow deletion of course reservations on class.</line>
				<line>Fix exceptions caused when inst offering limit and/or course offering limits are null.</line>
				<line>Course Reservations: On screen load - Do not add blank row if no. of reservations >= no. of courses in the offering.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Room Features and Groups</name>
			<description>
				<line>For global room features/groups: only display rooms from the current academic session.</line>
				<line>For departmental room features/groups: do not display rooms that are no longer shared by the feature's/group's department.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Data Export</name>
			<description>
				<line>Course offering and course timetable export added
					<line>DTDs CourseOfferingExport.dtd and CourseTimetable.dtd updated</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Custom Properties</name>
			<description>
				<line>Location of custom properties can be redefined by tmtbl.custom.properties property.
					<line>It can also be passed to JVM as a system property, e.g., -Dtmtbl.custom.properties=~/my.properties.</line></line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Other</name>
			<description>
				<line>Macromedia image files imported from the old Timetabling project.</line>
				<line>Constraint solver updated, see https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/cpsolver-cvs for more details.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>3.0.23</version>
	<release-date>Fri, 13 Jul 2007</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Rooms</name>
			<description>
				<line>For external manager with only one department (e.g., LAB) -- display the rooms of the department right away.</line>
				<line>Fixed display problem of departmental room features (sometimes, multiple features were displayed in a single row).</line>
				<line>Table ordering corrected (each table can be ordered separately, but only ordering of the class rooms table was actually used).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Rooms, Room Features, Room Groups</name>
			<description>
				<line>For external manager with only one department (e.g., LAB) -- display Export PDF button next to other buttons (Search/Export PDF component is not present).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Reservations</name>
			<description>
				<line>Removed color coding of total.</line>
				<line>Made changes pertaining to display of totals.</line>
				<line>Hide 'Add New' button as it is not useful</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Cross-lists</name>
			<description>
				<line>Removed color coding of total.</line>
				<line>Made changes pertaining to display of totals.</line>
				<line>Fixed bug deleted object will be resaved ...</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Departments</name>
			<description>
				<line>Fixed bug that makes abbv column un-sortable if any one value is null.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Subject Areas</name>
			<description>
				<line>Validate that subject area has no offered courses when delete operation is selected.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Menu</name>
			<description>
				<line>Use settings value to determine if menus are expanded on user login. By default it is not.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Course Timetabling</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added (optional) on fly student sectioning
					<line>In this mode, students are resectioned after each iteration, but only between classes that are affected by the iteration.</line>
					<line>This slows down the solver, but it can dramatically improve results in the case when there is more stress put on student conflicts (e.g., Woebegon College example).</line></line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Student Sectioning</name>
			<description>
				<line>Various fixes and improvements, see https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/cpsolver-cvs for more details.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Data Import</name>
			<description>
				<line>StudentImport and LastLikeCourseDemandImport are now inherited from BaseImport.</line>
				<line>StudentImport: speed improved by not using StudentDAO.save(student); all students for given academic session are deleted first</line>
				<line>LastLikeCourseDemandImport: all last-like course demands for given academic session are deleted first</line>
				<line>Data Import page now uploads the selected file (using Struts file upload).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Documentation</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added SQL scripts to create timetable schema and populate it with Woebegon College test suite for Oracle.</line>
				<line>Offline copy of UniTime wiki (http://www.unitime.org/wiki) added into the distribution.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Woebegon College test suite</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added on fly student sectioning solver parameters.</line>
				<line>Enabled on fly student sectioning in Default solver configuration.</line>
				<line>Enabled load of student enrollments for commited solutions in Default solver configuration.</line>
				<line>Added roomFeaturesInOneColumn user setting.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Other</name>
			<description>
				<line>Added methods for cloning of instructional offerings and all underlaying objects (configurations, subparts, classes, etc).</line>
				<line>ApplicationProperties: Removed shutdown hook since InitServlet.destroy() shuts the listener down; removed encoding from messages</line>
				<line>Changed timetabling banner to make consistent with the one used inside the application</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>3.0.22</version>
	<release-date>Wed, 27 Jun 2007</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>USER INTERFACE</title>
		<item>
			<name>Rooms</name>
			<description>
				<line>Room Features, Room Groups: Abbreviation column added</line>
				<line>Room Detail, Room Edit: Administrator can see and change external id.</line>
				<line>Room Detail, Room Edit: Administrator can change room type (property Room.scheduledRoomType).</line>
				<line>Allow Add Special Use Room only when external rooms are populated for the given session.</line>
				<line>Added add any room capability (administrator only).</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructional Offering Cross Lits</name>
			<description>
				<line>Made screen more intuitive.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Date Patterns</name>
			<description>
				<line>Display of the selected date pattern corrected.</line>
				<line>Fix Generated feature improved
					<line>replace the generated date pattern with an existing one if the difference is not more than 5 days</line>
					<line>otherwise rename the generated date pattern to "generated start - end" where start and end are start and end days in MM/dd format</line>
				</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Administration</name>
			<description>
				<line>Subject Areas: Struts configuration corrected.</line>
				<line>Buildings: Add/update/delete functions added.</line>
				<line>Buildings, Timetable Managers, Departments, Subject Areas, Solver Groups: Export PDF function added.</line>
				<line>Application Config: Display all effective properties set for the application.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Menu</name>
			<description>
				<line>FAQ and Tips &amp; Tricks pages moved to wiki.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Instructors</name>
			<description>
				<line>Instructor Lookup: Fixed problem with I2A2 lookup (No getter method for property: "puid" of bean: "i2a2") -- User object has no longer method getPuid(), but it has getId().</line>
				<line>Instructor Delete: Fixed hibernate problem (deleted object would be re-saved by cascade) when an instructor with some class assignments was deleted.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Distribution Preferences</name>
			<description>
				<line>Distribution preferences that are set on instructors were not filtered by course number, this is now corrected.</line>
				<line>Add/Edit Distribution Preference: Compare classes using ClassComparator, not by their unique ids.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<title>SOLVER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Student Sectioning</name>
			<description>
				<line>Load academic areas, classifications, majors, and minors</line>
				<line>Solver update, https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/cpsolver-cvs for more details.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<title>OTHER</title>
		<item>
			<name>Database</name>
			<description>
				<line>Database connection properties can be set in custom.property file</line>
				<line>Buildings: Minor change to remove non-existent building as part of update process.</line>
				<line>Major Import: Create empty set for academic areas if null.</line>
				<line>Configuration Edit: Fixed org.hibernate.PropertyAccessException (Exception occurred inside setter of org.unitime.timetable.model.Class_.managingDept)</line>
				<line>ChangeLog: queries made cacheable.</line>
				<line>Last-like Course Demands Import: speed up -- cache the SubjectAreas and CourseOfferings.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<name>Other</name>
			<description>
				<line>Timetabling CSS: Fixed a bug.</line>
				<line>WebTable: Removed italic tag and instead depend on css to do all formatting</line>
				<line>Changed logos to remove SMAS and put unitime.org.</line>
				<line>File footer.jsp removed -- it is not used.</line>
				<line>Tags propertyEquals and propertyNotEquals added.</line>
				<line>Use property tags instead of using ApplicationProperties class directly in JSPs.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

<release>
	<version>3.0.19</version>
	<release-date>Wed, 13 Jun 2007</release-date>
	<category>
		<title>ALL MODULES</title>
		<item>
			<name>First Open Source Release</name>
			<description>
				<line>This is a first Open Source release of this application.</line>
				<line>See http://www.unitime.org for more details.</line>
			</description>
		</item>
	</category>
</release>

</release-history>